<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Gareth Dwyer</title>
    <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/</link>
    <description>Gareth Dwyer (Posts)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 12:59:48 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>January 2021 Retrospective</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2021-01-january-retrospective/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 12:59:48 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2021-01-january-retrospective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🎉 We got our first ‘real’ MRR - $20/month!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🎉 We did a new product launch (writing job descriptions -&amp;gt; first revenue in under 48 hours!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🎉 We grew the team!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🐌 We failed to sign any new long term clients&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-first--mrr&#34;&gt;Our first (?) MRR!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of our clients are on month-to-month contracts. This means that we can fairly confidently predict our monthly recurring revenue, but it’s still manual. We do the work, send them an invoice, and hope that they don’t cancel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, I launched editing.ritza.co as an experiment. Many people I had spoken to wrote regularly, weren’t blown away by Grammarly, and wished they had a human editor, but didn’t really know how to get one. As we have several editors on retainers or similar agreements, it’s easy for us to generate spare editing capacity. I pushed the idea to a few people, and they were kind of interested, but not enough to put in their credit card details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reached out to someone I had done technical editing for before and who had ended the agreement as I was too expensive. He just needed more basic editing, but worked in markdown and GitHub and wrote about technical topics so the editor had to be at least somewhat technical. He trialed the service for free for a while last year and signed up in January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like our other clients, it’s still month-to-month and he can cancel any time he wants. That said, it’s set up as a Stripe recurring subscription so it feels more like ‘real’ MRR to me, even if it’s only $20/month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;writing-job-descriptions&#34;&gt;Writing job descriptions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever hung out with developers, you know how much they like to laugh at bad job descriptions. “We’re looking for a ninja rockstar” is the easiest way to get laughed at as an employer in 2021. Getting Java and Javascript mixed up is a close second. Asking for 10 years experience with some tech that’s only been around for 5 years also features. Writing job descriptions is actually hard: you’re trying to tell people about your requirements, but if you want good applicants, you also have to do this in a way that meets their requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw someone post on a Slack I’m part of, asking if anyone knew of a service that created job descriptions. I’ve written dozens of job descriptions for my ex-employer, several for Ritza, and I’ve read literally thousands of job descriptions (and seen how developers react to these) on ZATech slack. I put up &lt;a href=&#34;https://ritza.co/write-job-ads.html&#34;&gt;https://ritza.co/write-job-ads.html&lt;/a&gt; and sent it to him, and we reached an agreement the same day. We produced the first job ad the next day and got paid. We went on to do two more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think that ‘writing job ads’ will ever be a startup on its own, or necessarily something that we would like to double down on, but it was a great feeling to go from idea to cash in bank in 48 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;growing-the-team&#34;&gt;Growing the team&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the earliest pieces of advice I got when starting Ritza was ‘Make sure your first hire is an editor’. And I’ve definitely found myself backlogged by editing and finalising articles, as well as just keeping track of our commitments and the stages various things are at. I think one of our highest return long-term investments is also developmental editing - editing that focuses on helping the writer improve rather than on getting a piece finalised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were lucky to find an experienced editor with a background in publishing who had experience with machine learning content too. She joined us for the last week of January and is continuing part time in February.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also agreed to retainers with several more freelancers, and have several more in the pipeline, notably a front-end expert (which is where my own knowledge is most clearly in the ‘enough to be dangerous’ territory).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;no-new-clients&#34;&gt;No new clients&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re still growing slowly and organically and with as little outreach as possible. There were two seemingly very keen potential customers ‘in the pipe’ for December and January, so I focussed even less on outreach than usual, expecting either or both of these to confirm long term. Unfortunately, they are both quiet and slow (both are startups that recently did fairly large funding rounds, and I expect are battling with some of the growing pains and newly required process that I have seen other companies go through, where suddenly everything that was quick and easy becomes a lot slower and more difficult).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also had costs in January that were significantly higher than previous months. We are still profitable and remaining profitable will always be a core focus (otherwise I can’t eat), but we’ve now taken the nerve-wracking plunge of expecting some revenue growth in the next two months. Balancing finding more work with growing our team was always going to be a chicken-and-egg problem, and I’ve always been very risk-adverse. That said, I’m fairly confident that we’ve found some form of product market fit - we’ve seen that people need our services and I’m confident that we can find more with some effort, so I’m happy to build up the ‘supply’ side in anticipation, while shifting my personal focus more to the ‘demand’ side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;january-content-highlights&#34;&gt;January content highlights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We did the groundwork for “Go Hack Yourself a Portfolio” - an event we are running next week where devs can get together and work on their portfolios with some guidance and help from us and our tutorial on the same topic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We published a tutorial on Steganography that made the front page of news.ycombinator.com for a few hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zero to $50000 in six months: growing Ritza, a technical publishing company, as a productized service</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2020-retrospective/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 12:52:16 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2020-retrospective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For more background, you can find previous retrospectives for
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2019-retrospective/&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;2019&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2020-q1-retrospective/&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Q1
2020&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2020-04-retrospective/&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;April
2020&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2020-05-retrospective/&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;May
2020&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In July, I founded &lt;a href=&#34;https://ritza.co&#34;&gt;Ritza&lt;/a&gt; - a technical publishing company that offers
(very) technical content marketing, developer advocacy as a service, and
a bunch of related publishing services. What does that mean exactly? We
publish ebooks, documentation, and blog articles, usually with the goal
of helping developers or technical managers in some way. For example, we
did &lt;a href=&#34;https://codewithrepl.it&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;https://codewithrepl.it&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as a
companion website for &lt;a href=&#34;https://repl.it/&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Repl.it&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We offer this
content on a subscription basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title is clickbait: I’ve been working on Ritza for quite a bit
longer than 6 months, but it only became ‘real’ in July this year as a
registered business which I was devoting 100% of my time to, and &amp;ndash; from
what I’ve seen in Maker circles &amp;ndash; writing about how you got your
initial revenue is the best way to 2x your revenue, so the title is also
an experiment in some ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve gained a lot by reading about
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coryzue.com/open/&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;other&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SahinKevin/status/1334142235051520000&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;people’s&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://themakingof.carrd.co&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;transparent&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nomadlist.com/open&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;revenues&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That said, talking about
money is still weird for me, and I think it’s harder to be fully
transparent when offering services instead of a SaaS - there is more
customized pricing both in charging for work and paying contractors and
talking money is a sure way to get emotions up and make people feel like
they got a bad deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some high level figures for the last 6 months to get it out of
the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;revenue&#34;&gt;Revenue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ritza made between $6000 and $14000 revenue each month between July and
December, with a total revenue of around $58000 for the last two
quarters of 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was below my target of hitting $20000/month in 2020, but &amp;ndash;
especially given circumstances &amp;ndash; this was way better than my worst case
predictions. There was no clear overall trend, but a definite drop off
in November and December, with July and October being our best
performing months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of our contracts are month-to-month and one client went quiet in
October. While most of our revenue comes from recurring contracts, we
also did some one-off work in July through October, but none in November
or December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly all of our costs are from paying writers, editors, and designers.
We additionally spent money on office space that we don’t use (over
$500/month for coworking space that is tied to my ‘visa facilitation’,
which is a requirement for my visa in the Netherlands), and accounting
costs. We pay a few dollars a month for various online services, such as
GSuite and various domains, and we have credits on DigitalOcean and AWS
which take care of all of our hosting for now. We also recently picked
up a subscription to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.semrush.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;SemRush&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - a tool
that I think is overpriced and slightly shady, but which has proven its use
in better understanding what people are searching for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, this revenue allows me to pay myself a ‘salary’ that pays rent
in Europe, with more cash than my previous job as Head of Technology for
a South African EdTech startup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, my plan B after quitting my previous role was to find a full
time job remotely or in Europe. I shopped around a bit and did some
interviews for roles that were offering $150k-$200k/year + benefits so
in terms of opportunity cost I am still ‘losing’ for now and it remains
to be seen how far Ritza can scale with its current business model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;experiments-and-content&#34;&gt;Experiments and content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our bread-and-butter service is producing technical content: writing
&lt;a href=&#34;https://codewithrepl.it&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;tutorials&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://datarevenue.com/en-blog&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;blog&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://virtasant.com/blog/data-lake-vs-data-warehouse/&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;content&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
While our mission is to unlock marketing budgets “for good” by making
this content available for free, we have also helped companies produce
and improve internal proprietary content that they then sell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the side, I have been playing around with the idea of building online
tools to help with producing and publishing content. None of these got
the attention they needed to get off the ground, but they remain on the
back burner as ideas I’d still like to work on. They included&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://vsgraphs.ritza.co/&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;‘vs’ Graphs&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/strong&gt; a tool
inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/applied-data-science/the-google-vs-trick-618c8fd5359f&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;this
article&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
I built this because I needed it - especially for writing articles
about ‘hot’ spaces like MLOps and DevOps, it’s easy to get
overwhelmed by the sheer number of tools, products, and services.
This visualisation makes it easy to explore a new area and find
the most popular products, as well as to find out how a specific
product ‘fits in’ (“Oh X plays in the same space as SageMaker”).
This is also useful to write ‘&lt;a href=&#34;https://datarevenue.com/en-blog/data-dashboarding-streamlit-vs-dash-vs-shiny-vs-voila&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;x vs y vs
z&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’
articles, which turn out to be very low hanging fruit in terms of
ranking well on Google. If you’ve ever tried to find out how two
products or services compare and found yourself frustrated at all
the low quality ‘alternativeTo-like’ pages you’ll know why these
articles are useful, and I ended up also building a &lt;a href=&#34;http://versus.ritza.co&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;related
tool&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to outline these articles
automatically. The fun part about this was that I built it in a
single train ride using only my iPad and repl.it, which felt like
a big step in the direction of being able to code as a nomad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ratemycopy.ritza.co/&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Rate my Copy&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Also while
researching products and services, I got annoyed at how cliched
most landing page copy is, and even more annoyed by how
uninformative it is. I scraped over 20000 landing pages for online
products and services and built a database of the most commonly
used cliches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ritza.co/experiments/opinionated-tutorial-publisher.html&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Opinionated tutorial
Publisher&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -
while most of our clients have their own systems already in place
to host the content we produce, I was frustrated at how hard it
was to generate a lightweight, good looking page with writing,
code samples, and images. There’s a long way to go on the design
still, but some of the other pieces are in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won’t link to all the content we produced in 2020, but some highlights
are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codewithrepl.it/&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;CodeWithRepl.it&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/strong&gt; a set
of tutorials, also in book form. This was very well received on
reddit and continues to rank well for a variety of search terms. I
am strongly against most kinds of tracking, but caved at the end
of the year and installed Plausible Analytics on it, which also
makes it easy to share publicly everything we track:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://plausible.io/codewithrepl.it&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;https://plausible.io/codewithrepl.it&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
Traffic has died off a lot at the end of the year (based on some
server logs analytics I did), but rankings continue to improve and
I think the content is in pretty good shape now (we’ve done
several sets of updates since initially publishing it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://datarevenue.com/en-blog&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;DataRevenue Blog&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -
This is the project I’ve personally learned the most from this
year, writing about everything from general machine learning
through BioTech (I didn’t even know what Metabolomics was in 2019,
so there was a steep learning curve to write some of the articles
about that).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;growing-a-team&#34;&gt;Growing a team&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we initially mainly worked ad-hoc with contractors on various
projects, towards the end of the year Ritza started feeling like a real
company with a core team. &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/eugenedorfling/technical-writing-internship-it-can-only-get-better-from-here-10ma&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Eugene
Dorfling&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
joined in October for a full time internship and is continuing in 2021
as an Associate Developer Advocate. Several other freelancers have
regularly worked on projects throughout the year. I’m still trying to
figure out if the next full time hire should be a senior writer (to take
over some of the writing I am doing), or a managing editor (to help out
with client feedback and all the nitty-gritty but super important
aspects of getting from ‘first draft’ to ‘production’), but I’m leaning
more towards the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-ritza&#34;&gt;What IS Ritza?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friends and family still don’t really understand what Ritza is. I get a
lot of “uh, so you make IT manuals, right? Isn’t that just telling
people to turn stuff off and on again until it works?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ritza is probably closest to a ‘content marketing agency’ at this stage.
But I really dislike most content marketing agencies. Not to name and
shame, but there’s definitely decent demand for very low cost content
such as
&lt;a href=&#34;https://contentfly.com/blog/tag/content-sample/&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;https://contentfly.com/blog/tag/content-sample/&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
and I honestly can’t see how that adds any value to the world at all, so
I want to avoid being pulled in that direction or associated with
content like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My initial response to this was to try to move towards “Developer
Advocacy as a Service”, but it doesn’t really roll off the tongue, and
I’m not sure that “Developer Advocacy” is actually a job that will
survive the Tech Bubble I’m convinced we’re in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the year, it became clear that Ritza is simply a
publishing company (or at least the very beginnings of one). We are
slowly becoming experts in the entire publishing pipeline, from sourcing
high quality writing, through editing, designing, publishing, and
distributing. While we have started out with a strong focus on technical
content, there’s no reason that that has to remain a core focus forever.
I’ve had pretty mediocre experiences with technical publishing companies
like PacktPub and I believe non-tech publishers that have existed for
decades or centuries are even more in need of a bit of modernization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I previously helped my Dad publish his first book of (hilarious)
&lt;a href=&#34;http://leanpub.com/doctor&#34;&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;memoirs as a Doctor in Africa&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and
during the slower period between Christmas and New Year now I spent some
time tweaking the landing page, making a sample available, and doing
some marketing. So far, all I’ve done is burn $50 on Reddit ads that led
to zero sales, but I think with some experimentation with different
distribution channels there’s more potential. Stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2020 05 Retrospective</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2020-05-retrospective/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 12:41:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2020-05-retrospective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;May 2020 was my last month trying to launch Ritza while being full-time employed. My last month (hopefully ever!) as a full time employee was fairly busy with handovers and whatnot and this impacted progress on Ritza, so I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to being able to stop splitting focus (spoiler for next month&amp;rsquo;s retro, the first week has been pretty great!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;launching-ritzaco-the-two-kinds-of-feedback&#34;&gt;Launching ritza.co: the two kinds of feedback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I launched &lt;a href=&#34;https://ritza.co&#34;&gt;ritza.co&lt;/a&gt; in May. It&amp;rsquo;s &amp;hellip; rough &amp;hellip; to say the least, and the initial feedback I got from family and friends was brutally honest. &amp;ldquo;I still don&amp;rsquo;t get what it is?&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Why are there no pictures?&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Uh, maybe take a design course or something? Here&amp;rsquo;s a coupon.&amp;rdquo; etc etc. While Ritza aims to take a strong stance &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ldquo;marketing websites&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;SEO strategies&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;call to action buttons&amp;rdquo;, and all of those other good things, I am not planning on the landing page looking like that forever. The copy is not great for a start, and it&amp;rsquo;s undoubtedly ugly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I posted the link in ZATech slack, news.ycombinator.com, and the EUTech telegram group. I got one comment on HN (it shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have been on &amp;ldquo;Show HN&amp;rdquo; anyway as it&amp;rsquo;s not something anyone can &amp;ldquo;play with&amp;rdquo; yet.), a bunch of good discussion from EUTech, including some people saying that their companies were looking for Tech content, and a few comments from people who already knew something about Ritza on ZATech. The feedback was unanimously negative about the landing page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rebel in me wanted to see if Ritza could be successful &lt;em&gt;in spite&lt;/em&gt; of an ugly landing page (playing on hard mode?) and as I spent most of May juggling needs from my employer and two Ritza clients anyway, improving the landing page was not the top of my to do list. But I also wondered if I was shooting myself in the foot. It&amp;rsquo;s obviously in my best interest for people to get a good first impression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days later, I came across &lt;a href=&#34;FounderSummit&#34;&gt;https://foundersummit.co/&lt;/a&gt; again. I&amp;rsquo;ve been following &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/tylertringas&#34;&gt;Tyler Tringas&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for a while, and while I was initially very skeptical of the &amp;ldquo;funding for bootstrappers&amp;rdquo; paradox, I&amp;rsquo;ve found his posts interesting and authentic. I signed up for the FounderSummit community of getting an email saying that it was free for a limited period.I posted a short introduction and a link to Ritza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As there were under 100 people in this &amp;ldquo;paid&amp;rdquo; slack community, I was expecting exactly 0 response. I was surprised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/hugoblog/resources/slackintro.png&#34; alt=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within hours I had received a bunch of positive feedback and had set up several introduction calls with potential customers who wanted to hear more. People told me they were excited about the idea, could see the need for the service, and wanted to work together. Not a single person mentioned the (lack of) design, or ugly landing page. It was a pretty strong contrast from the &amp;ldquo;friends and family&amp;rdquo; launch and it was great to get the positive reinforcement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t signed any new deals from these intros yet so take the seeming success with a pinch of salt,  but I have met some good people, had some good conversations, and I am waiting for some &amp;ldquo;leads&amp;rdquo; to get back to me still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-got-published&#34;&gt;What got published&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked on some more Python notebooks, and had a lot of fun playing with some global energy datasets (did you know that South Africa is one of the few countries in the world to see the amount of energy going towards rail &lt;em&gt;drop&lt;/em&gt; over the last 20 years? I didn&amp;rsquo;t). I edited several of these notebooks and created on from scratch. It was fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am working on several things for another client, but due to various factors (including me being slow), none of them are published yet. I decided to delay my May invoice for them until they have published at least some of the May work, so Ritza revenue is down a lot. (I&amp;rsquo;m expecting to still invoice them for May and June and to count the first invoice as part of May revenue, so this is hopefully a temporary situation.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;publishing-tools-and-services&#34;&gt;Publishing tools and services&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also started experimenting with micro SaaS-like tools, which I am expecting Ritza to build and release regularly over the next few years. The first one is an &lt;a href=&#34;https://ritza.co/experiments/opinionated-tutorial-publisher.html&#34;&gt;Opinionated Tutorial Publisher&lt;/a&gt;. I have spent so much time messing around with different themes (HTML, Ghost, Hugo, etc) as well as with Pandoc flags, different markup formats, etc, that I wished there was just a tool that had no options, no themes, and &amp;ldquo;just worked&amp;rdquo;. There is still a lot of room for improvement, but the MVP of this was something that could turn markdown into HTML and handle text, images, and code samples in a nice way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m now working on another SaaS-like tool too. This analyses landing page copy and finds common cliches, patterns in adjective, verb, and noun use, sentence length, etc. I scraped around 20000 landing pages and built an initial dataset. I&amp;rsquo;m still doing a lot of cleaning and analysing, but here&amp;rsquo;s a sneak preview (which should also technically be part of next month&amp;rsquo;s retro, but I thought it was pretty cool), showing how many sites use the phrase &amp;ldquo;makes it easy to&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/hugoblog/resources/easyto.gif&#34; alt=&#34;easy to&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;goals&#34;&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;June is going by fast already. By the end of June I hope to have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Signed at least one more client&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launched one more SaaS-like service (probably for free, but something that has the potential to grow into something I could start charging for), probably based around landing page copy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Signed a contract with a Dutch Startup Facilitator to help secure a visa.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>April 2020 Retrospective</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2020-04-retrospective/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 17:55:30 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2020-04-retrospective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I did a &lt;a href=&#34;https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2020-q1-retrospective/&#34;&gt;2020 Q1 retrospective&lt;/a&gt; pretty late, so this is more focused on the 10-30 April period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ritza-progress&#34;&gt;Ritza progress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ritza is still evolving at what feels like a slow pace. I launched &lt;a href=&#34;ritza.co&#34;&gt;ritza.co&lt;/a&gt; today (actually it has been live for a while, but it had a brain dump on the homepage which I rewrote today to have more structure and provide more relevant information). I shared it on ZATech, HackerNews, and the EUTech telegram group and got some good feedback (thank you if you were one of the people that provided this!), which I am integrating into the next iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am still in some contact with two &amp;ldquo;startup facilitators&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; organizations in the Netherlands which can endorse startups which I need for my visa. Unfortunately both are very slow to respond to my emails, so I keep assuming that they are no longer interested, only to get a reply once I have given up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other miscelaneous bits of progress include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying to sign up for MailChimp again but realising I had already used the single &amp;ldquo;audience&amp;rdquo; for a test page I launched (startyourown.co) and then abandoned, so signing up for ConvertKit instead. Both are companies firmly in the marketing world that I consider at least slightly email (tracking, targeted advertising etc), but I do not want to sink the time needed into building my own mailing list system at this stag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having the deck I mentioned in the previous post designed on fiverr - I wasn&amp;rsquo;t super excited about the result but it&amp;rsquo;s not terrible either and was good enough for what I needed it for. You can see it &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1uFljO1odpS9oyaTHY0uA4wO63WX_r_H6buEulXJzYPY/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Telling various people about Ritza and getting feedback. I did a mini-pitch and discussion for Ritza to two informal meetup groups, both through ZATech, and got some positive feedback on the concept (yay!) and some advice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I started a &amp;ldquo;Zettelkasten&amp;rdquo; system based on the advice of &lt;a href=&#34;https://cpbotha.net/&#34;&gt;CP Botha&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m still trying to figure out exactly to best use it and I am currently maintaining both a physical version with pen and paper and a digital version (I think the double entry actually helps instil the notes mentally too, but I only have 12 or so thus far so we&amp;rsquo;ll see).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;revenue&#34;&gt;Revenue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous post, I mentioned I was on track to make $6000 in revenue for April. I ended up invoicing $5600 in revenue in the end after having to end a relationship with one client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had already agreed to something significantly below my usual rate for a trial article to &amp;ldquo;build the relationship&amp;rdquo; and had a good call with the CEO of the company to discuss the goals for the piece. Things seemed fairly promising until I submitted a 100 word or so outline as requested (basically just headings and a short description of what would be in each) and got dozens of nitpicky comments in response &amp;ndash; their editor spent over 2 hours (based on the Google docs comments timestamps) making comments about style, capitalization, American spelling conventions, etc etc. Maybe she was just very thorough but I took it badly and it felt like the comments were coming from an egotistical place rather than a supportive one, so I decided that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t worth the time or emotional energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-got-published&#34;&gt;What got published&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I spent many hours on editing a Python data science tutorial which had some pretty obscure and frustrating bugs and took way longer to fix than I had estimated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also wrote &lt;a href=&#34;https://datarevenue.com/en-blog/machine-learning-for-managers&#34;&gt;Machine learning for managers&lt;/a&gt;, which again hit rank #1 on Google after 48 hours for the search term &lt;code&gt;Machine Learning for Managers&lt;/code&gt; and is now hovering between #1 and #3 for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I compiled my first &lt;a href=&#34;https://ritza.co/showcase/repl.it&#34;&gt;showcase&lt;/a&gt;. This involved downloading the original sources, cleaning up some of the markdown, finding a pandoc workflow that works for me (at the moment it&amp;rsquo;s markdown -&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;.adoc&lt;/code&gt; (asciidoctor) using pandoc and then .adoc -&amp;gt; html using asciidoctor and the Ruby CSS stylesheet with highlight.js and the Monokai theme (which seems to be the only one that highlights a decent number of Python keywords). Once I have a publication pipeline better put together I&amp;rsquo;ll publish a separate article on that. I also am editing the collection into a book format (currently downloadable as an ebook from the showcase page, but I&amp;rsquo;m adding an introduction, removing external links, and linking the chapters together more cohesively still).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-next&#34;&gt;Where next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still trying to get the legal and tax side of everything set up. Progress is frustratingly slow. I also have a todo list which currently contains things such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collecting the rest of my content from around the web to combine it into more &amp;ldquo;showcases&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extending the homepage and additional pages to answer more questions people have (what kind of content do you produce?, why is it so expensive?, is this marketing?, why should I buy this? are some at the moment)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding an &amp;ldquo;/open&amp;rdquo; dashboard (I was going to link to the popular Baremetrics page here but then I discovered that they link to &amp;ldquo;Hubstaff&amp;rdquo; which provides malware to allow employers to spy on their employees so I won&amp;rsquo;t)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t expect things to change too much in the next 4 weeks while I am still spending a majority of my time at my full time job, but I hope to set more ambitious monthly goals from 1 June!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2020 Q1 Retrospective</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2020-q1-retrospective/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 16:12:10 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2020-q1-retrospective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A large part of my 2019 retrospective focused on Ritza: a concept I have been playing with which aims to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Produce high quality technical tutorials and articles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow companies to buy and publish these tutorials (hopefully instead of buying targeted advertising)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pay full time writers, editors, programmers, and designers to produce this content at scale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also talked about some other stuff like visas and leaving South Africa, but I’ll focus on Ritza progress in this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;proving-demand-and-finding-a-business-model&#34;&gt;Proving demand and finding a business model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent a lot of time last year thinking about what Ritza was and how it would work. I focused a lot on the production or supply side. How would I find writers? What would my agreement with them look like? How would designers, editors, and technical quality assurance fit into this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t fully solve any of the problems I was thinking about, but I walked pretty deep into some of these rabbit holes. I’m confident enough that I could put the supply side together pretty quickly if necessary, especially as I can one-man the supply side fairly well on my own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, I switched more to focus on the demand side. “Technical articles are great and you should buy some” sounds good to me, but I expect real customers to be a bit harder to sell to than imaginary ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of still having “side project” status, I’m pretty pleased with how well Ritza has been doing in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For April 2020, I have $6000 in revenue booked (although I’m writing this on 10 April, it’s unlikely that this will change as I still need to write a lot of this booked content and wouldn’t accept more work at this stage).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For comparison, in the whole of 2019 I generated $8864 in revenue (this actually came from various sources, but for simplicity I’ll bucket it all under “Ritza”, aka “not my full time job”), and for January-March 2020 I generated $4500.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More exciting than the amounts to me is finding my first client who fits (almost) perfectly into Ritza’s proposed model: a monthly subscription and public content. Ritza’s first “real” client agreed to a $3000/month fee (initially for 3 months) to produce around 4000 words of content a month - slightly lower than the rate I aim for, but I’m very happy to be flexible as I start off with this model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-content-got-produced-so-far-in-2020&#34;&gt;What content got produced so far in 2020?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my ideal vision of Ritza, I would get to decide what content to produce, how to license it, and where to publish it. Nearly all the content would educate readers on how to build something using code, and it would all be released under an MIT license with readers being able to make pull requests to improve it. Customers would pay a fixed monthly fee for this content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the real world, customers have opinions too, so I’m still quite far from that &amp;ldquo;dream model&amp;rdquo;. I’ve written for four clients in 2020 so far, and only one has been close to the “Ritza model”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;packtpub&#34;&gt;PacktPub&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first contract of the year was with PacktPub, a book publishing company that I’ve written for before. They asked me to write 3 chapters for a book on “Data Storage for Artificial Intelligence”. I hesitantly agreed even though the money was not amazing because&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of the chapters was about the Ethics of AI, and I enjoy the topic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I knew from experience that I would be assigned an editor who would be super pushy about deadlines and breathe (virtually) down my neck, forcing me to write, which is something that’s still helpful for getting the quantity of writing output I’m aiming for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book was meant to be published in March but due to various factors is now due to be published on 28 April (not my fault this time!), so I can’t link to this content yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;codementor-and-arc&#34;&gt;CodeMentor and Arc&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CodeMentor, one of my earliest clients, partially rebranded to Arc last year. They keep separate blogs under both brands, with the former having an audience of software developers, and the latter of managers and technical hirers. I wrote one piece on remote working for each blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arc.dev/blog/transition-remote-engineering-team-965iuuiidx&#34;&gt;CTO&amp;rsquo;s Cheat Sheet: Transition to a Remote Engineering Team Right Now&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codementor.io/blog/dev-wfh-94omq9htht&#34;&gt;5 Actionable Tips For Developers Suddenly Working From Home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not especially proud of either of these pieces. There are no shortage of similar articles and I don’t think I could provide any new or interesting insights, but it’s what the client wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;datarevenue&#34;&gt;DataRevenue&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found DataRevenue via a service called “The Writer Finder”. This is a writer matching service where clients describe the content they’re looking for and The Growth Machine (the company behind The Writer Finder) puts out a description to their “network” of writers, playing matchmaker. I signed up ages ago out of curiosity, but I’ve never used them before as all of the requests are usually for non-technical content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked with DataRevenue to produce this article &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.datarevenue.com/en-blog/machine-learning-covid-19&#34;&gt;How to fight COVID-19 with machine learning&lt;/a&gt; (I was one of several people working on it), and we were happy when it reached the top spot of Google for “Machine Learning covid-19” very shortly after publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;misc&#34;&gt;Misc&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also worked with a long-standing client to produce data science tutorials, especially on SQL and NLP. My work here is non-public and involves both writing new tutorials and editing existing ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;whats-next&#34;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m happy with the progress so far, but I’m not claiming “product market fit” quite yet. I’m hoping to find more clients who are willing to pay on a monthly basis for a fixed word count. At the moment, I can still produce all of the content myself, but I’m definitely pushing the limits of late night writing again, so I am starting to look for a junior writing assistant to help with coordination, writing, and editing. I have not thought about how this would work exactly, but I expect to offer someone around R10000/month for 20h/week on some kind of learnership or internship kind of agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more pressing problem is to figure out tax and company structure. So far, all of this has been done by me as an individual, using services like PayPal. I’m currently living in Europe by still paying tax in South Africa where I am employed full time, so things get a bit complicated. I’m still persuing different visa options (my current visa will end in August which is coming up worryingly fast, especially with most administrative procedures delayed until further notice right now), but my goals for Q2 2020 include registering a Dutch BV (private company) and sorting out my current tax status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the requirements for one of the visas I am applying for is to have an &amp;ldquo;accredited faciliator&amp;rdquo; to provide coaching. In order to get one of these, I need a pitch deck. While I would rather avoid the &amp;ldquo;startup-y&amp;rdquo; things as much as possible, I could definitely use help on the tax and business administration side and this is something a faciliator provides. On the downside, it means I have to create the pitch deck. I am definitely not a designer. My attempt is &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1cVyuckLFdoi1MPTv7Mkio_5ILUYXrqXxJVOdGrio1d4/edit#slide=id.g710e417310_0_4&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and if anyone reading this is visually offended (I am) and knows how to make it better, please let me know! [Update, I paid someone on Fiverr to clean it up for me and was pretty happy with the results &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1uFljO1odpS9oyaTHY0uA4wO63WX_r_H6buEulXJzYPY/edit#slide=id.p1&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll also try move to monthly updates going forwards (and eventually to weekly?).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2019 Retrospective</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2019-retrospective/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 13:49:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2019-retrospective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People overestimate what can be done in one year and underestimate what can be done in ten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://quoteinvestigator.com/2019/01/03/estimate/&#34;&gt;Someone, probably&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quote above gets thrown around a lot in my circles, but I think it is useful in several ways. Most people are too concerned with short term value, too ambitious with their short term goals, and unwilling to stick at something for very long. This bias leads companies to focus too heavily on monthly or quarterly (or weekly!) goals, and individuals to avoid taking on ambitious projects. The end of 2019 saw a lot of people posting 10 year retrospectives and reading these is a great way to put into perspective what can be achieved in 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all a preface to me admitting that I didn’t achieve as much in 2019 as I would have liked to, but taking comfort in the fact that my goals for 2020 are similar to what they were a year ago, and some progress has been made, so I’m looking forward to the next 12 months. One bite at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main themes of 2019 that I’m covering in this post are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side projects, passive income, and Ritza&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I write and do other things by moonlight for money, mainly because I enjoy it, but also because it pays enough to keep me in software engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moving to Europe and applying for many visas, getting some rejections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving is difficult and governments will keep asking for more paperwork until the Amazon forests runs out. Read about this section if you’re interested in leaving South Africa without a second passport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reading about finance, economics, politics, and startups&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read less than I wanted to this year, but one or two highlights stuck out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;side-projects-passive-income-and-education&#34;&gt;Side projects, passive income, and education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018, I focussed on writing &lt;a href=&#34;http://dwyer.co.za/writing.html&#34;&gt;technical tutorials&lt;/a&gt; by moonlight. I enjoy writing these as I get paid but the content I produce is made available for free, which seems like a win-win. Last year, I continued writing for various clients under different models and also did technical interviewing for Karat for a few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it strange to talk about money in public places, but at the same time I have benefited a lot from other people sharing data openly under the &lt;a href=&#34;https://hackernoon.com/what-does-it-mean-to-be-an-open-startup-f4446984189&#34;&gt;Open Startups&lt;/a&gt; ideology, so for anyone who is interested, here are some key numbers from 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made on average $739/month, which just about pays my rent in Cape Town (first half of the year) or Zurich (second half). This is from various sources, but mainly from the technical writing I do by moonlight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/z1aTsSFwrQJWTzabWmOGRVOR8BpGg6ArRb1TqJCCr29HqoFfF01V8ew4HfrKcZttsOlwyQYAKYfwadRnC-1zaeWDyZO3E18CFekn9lyQfWMz-H0RJULeJjGYfal8oPfUxU3ca0xy&#34; alt=&#34;img&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Half of the amount in the ‘writing’ category is from a single project (instructional content on SQL) where the result was not made publically available. Due to this, I charged more than usual. The rest was made up of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Four blog posts for CodeMentor on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codementor.io/blog/geolocation-6ufm6uk91n&#34;&gt;IP GeoLocation&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codementor.io/blog/text-classification-6mmol0q8oj&#34;&gt;Text Classification&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codementor.io/blog/batch-endpoints-6olbjay1hd&#34;&gt;Batch endpoints for Rest APIs&lt;/a&gt;, and a post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://arc.dev/blog/transition-team-to-remote-work-8mkqhumgxt&#34;&gt;transitioning your team to remote working&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One blog post on Arc (previously CodeMentor) on &lt;a href=&#34;https://arc.dev/blog/devops-interview-guide-8bb0470rqz&#34;&gt;interviewing DevOps Candidates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One short guest post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.computerweekly.com/blog/CW-Developer-Network/AI-developer-toolset-series-Codementor-on-AI-tooling-vs-theory&#34;&gt;Tooling vs Theory for AI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two posts for Repl on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codementor.io/@garethdwyer/introduction-to-machine-learning-with-python-and-repl-it-rln7ywkhc&#34;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codementor.io/@garethdwyer/building-news-word-clouds-using-python-and-repl-it-sy7l88roq&#34;&gt;Building WordClouds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also wrote a post &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codementor.io/@garethdwyer/writing-and-process-how-to-be-a-technical-writer-without-getting-stuck-s344bu38y&#34;&gt;about writing&lt;/a&gt; which no one paid for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relatedly, I bought one of the last offered ‘lifetime subscriptions’ for &lt;a href=&#34;https://leanpub.com/&#34;&gt;https://leanpub.com/&lt;/a&gt; and I hope to use this to publish longer form content in 2020. I used it to help my father edit and self-publish his first memoir, which is available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://leanpub.com/doctor,&#34;&gt;https://leanpub.com/doctor,&lt;/a&gt; and learned a lot about the publishing industry and publishing tools in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ‘editing’ section in the breakdown above is also from CodeMentor, and involves briefly reviewing and commenting on a post outline from another writer and then doing one round of suggestions on the first draft. It does not take very long, and I enjoy reading other people’s work, so I always agree to requests from them even though the money hardly makes it worth the coordination time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, having my posts scattered around the internet instead of all as “Codementor Community Articles” (tracked in the stats below) meant that my &amp;lsquo;tracked&amp;rsquo; growing readership did not keep pace with what I saw in 2018. I only published 4 new articles on this main platform. More reasons for the dwindling numbers come down to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of traffic was driven by a single post: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codementor.io/@garethdwyer/flask-vs-django-why-flask-might-be-better-4xs7mdf8v&#34;&gt;Flask vs Django&lt;/a&gt; which was top of Google for related search results for some time, but has now dropped down to the third or fourth result&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CodeMentor themselves pivoted away from education and into recruitment, rebranding to Arc. I guess this means they are giving less attention to their community platform, and more readers are moving to platforms like HackerNoon and Dev.to to find tutorials. I hope to explore writing on these platforms in 2020, but I have my problems with both of them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My posts on my CodeMentor profile got only 300’000 new views and I gained only 250 new followers in 2019. I had expected well over a million views in 2019, so this was a good reminder that past performance does not predict future results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My CodeMentor readership stats as of January 2020:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/kB21Q_wl_PcOBdwt7E3juNh15rMm-SkN3p3Nqk2uW_y13R4DT8T_JOkwBaaDJ-qCR5TglnpKP0pCKyGRDm8-RrrusQALIlj-l3BB3VQ0-0KRq5l58lvRWHkCmPkbO6c9TMtXQR_R&#34; alt=&#34;img&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stats from my previous retrospective, January 2019, for comparison:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/weBtRvDqB1MX62lHuTq57eY0zAM7PgpFy6FlcTVFl8590L-4LwVwg8LOJn_pEv2lNGaaE508r8Bvjt4Z5EiU-IomT2-VFDhc2qWtfZb6BigiH173TwZbCOT8t6ZiD-jv5Lh0SlDs&#34; alt=&#34;img&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;technical-interviewing&#34;&gt;Technical interviewing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technical interviewing section in the breakdown above was from my brief stint as a Technical Interviewer at Karat. It was lots of fun, very educational, and Karat was exceptional in providing really high quality materials to learn how to interview using their method and in providing a great and super friendly community of interviewers around the globe. I learned some valuable skills in objective assessment and making people feel comfortable in interviews, which I hope to keep honing long term. I unfortunately had to stop as I found the interviews very tiring (one hour of 1:1 interaction followed by around 30 minutes of writing up a report), and I was attempting to do them usually during the week after a day of fighting with hard technical problems, while juggling emigration (more on that later). Nonetheless, I would strongly recommend taking a look at Karat.com if you are interested in earning around $70/hour for very flexible remote work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;royalties&#34;&gt;Royalties&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The non-best selling video course I published in 2014 with PacktPub, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.packtpub.com/eu/application-development/rapid-flask-video&#34;&gt;Rapid Flask&lt;/a&gt;, continues to be a non-best seller. Ditto for &lt;a href=&#34;https://flaskbyexample.com/&#34;&gt;Flask by Example &lt;/a&gt;which was published in 2016. These make up my only source of passive income, which has now dwindled to an impressive average of $50/month, which just about covers my various domain names and other hosting costs for side projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is all the data about the royalties I earn through the video and book. Although this income is ‘passive’ in the sense that I don’t have to do any work and I get a small amount of money deposited in my bank every quarter, it’s not really passive. The book took a huge number of hours to write and produce, and I was given only a small advance of $3000, so in reality this money is still paying off my hours from a few years ago, and will likely hit zero before that hourly rate becomes reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/g30MR74o08YLYDr4kJJ8eftRKD18I1wvbfjvbHymX-BL3BoZWEkpKuPdjgH3tH-37CVtcD2PqxCvnRWCoJYWd3yN47KPxTkbpa9RIFrbsQ3dKZ6XpA0NAkJmkTtjuZrvwRRUJeel&#34; alt=&#34;img&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/aAKR1dMu_Knmf57jhoqhOaf-D1x6k-sARUNnUwsEOJJ8aNm1TlJKgYIDSgil_jX_PHB6aGR5B1vOpuojZEZhML5auftbr6bgfqUpIQtLU1wDJ1z1wbuTrhIRmmg74xSZNu1ZB56u&#34; alt=&#34;img&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal since 2017 has been to hit $2000/&lt;strong&gt;month&lt;/strong&gt; in passive income, and each year has taken me further away from that goal. I don’t believe I will be able to reverse the trend in 2020 within the constraints of full time employment, but I will continue to actively explore ideas and experiment on as many of them as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ritza&#34;&gt;Ritza&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019, I found myself obsessing over the ‘win-win’ I described above a lot: getting paid for content that is released for free. I wonder how this could be scaled to something larger than just me staring at my laptop long into the evening, pretending to write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been so many attempts to get consumers to pay for content at scale over the last decade, but in spite of micropayments from Brave, large and intrusive begging pop-ups from The Guardian and Wikipedia, harder paywalls from the likes of WSJ, NYT, and Bloomberg, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/JohnONolan/status/1186634031498088451&#34;&gt;some people finding success with individual publishing&lt;/a&gt;, consumers are as unwilling as ever to pay for what they read, even if it’s educational. And why should they? Companies plough trillions of dollars into targeted digital advertising, which many people predict is non-sustainable, and it is no secret that one of the best ways to win customers in many areas is to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ecorner.stanford.edu/in-brief/out-teach-your-competition/&#34;&gt;share knowledge with them for free&lt;/a&gt; (or even without that being that radical, traditional marketing departments continue to cry that ‘content is king’ for SEO while producing shallow clickbait content that has a negative shelf life). At the same time, location independent work is on the rise, people are realising that it’s OK to have a life outside of work with ‘work-life balance’ being a hot topic. And there still remains a strong division between ‘arts’ and ‘science’ disciplines, enforced by most universities globally, meaning that many technology experts battle to write, and many great writers think that they are ‘fundamentally not technical’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the above, I think there is a huge opportunity in a service that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Employs technical experts and writing experts on a flexible, fully remote, 20h/week schedule&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creates a publishing pipeline of topic -&amp;gt; drafts -&amp;gt; writing and coding -&amp;gt; editing -&amp;gt; technical checking -&amp;gt; copy editing -&amp;gt; design and publishing to create ‘10x content’ that unbiasedly educates readers about technology topics while showcasing the features of specific products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gets the companies of the above products to pay $$$ for the privilege of being featured in the high quality educational articles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several times this year I tried to write down more details on how this could look, but writing is hard. I bought a cheap domain name, ritza.co, to give all of these ideas somewhere public to live in the hope that it would attract like minded people who would be willing to listen to me ramble and further develop the ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ritza is very much a working title which I expect to change if I ever use it, but out of interest the name comes from&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;‘Rit’ (‘go slow’ as a direction given to musicians)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;‘za’ from South Africa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;‘Ritz’ which is a brand that I have no first hand experience with but which I associate with high quality (people have since told me it’s icky and kitsch).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of my attempted drafts of a ‘pitch’ for this idea are at&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ritza.co&#34;&gt;ritza.co&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ritza.co/content/pitch5&#34;&gt;https://ritza.co/content/pitch5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ritza.co/content/pitch4&#34;&gt;https://ritza.co/content/pitch4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even rougher material at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sixhobbits/ritza&#34;&gt;https://github.com/sixhobbits/ritza&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My final public technical tutorials for 2019 was a proof of concept to see if this idea could potentially sustain itself. I decided that the ‘MVP’ of Ritza was to coordinate at least three people:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A writer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An editor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A client&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writer or editor would have to wear a few different hats as the initial model has different people for QA, copy editing, design, etc, but the core process is to give a topic to the writer, have the result improved by the editor, and sell it to the client. I wanted the topic to be educational in nature and made available to the public for free, while covering its costs (including at least some of my time).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily I already had some clients, and knew some people with expertise in technology and writing who could help out with editing. I advertised on ZATech Slack for a writer and after a drawn out but informal interview process selected someone who had some technical writing experience and some coding experience. The whole process took a couple of months which was slower than freelancing writing by myself, but it worked! The result is at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codementor.io/@garethdwyer/building-a-crm-app-with-nodejs-repl-it-and-mongodb-119r72mczg&#34;&gt;https://www.codementor.io/@garethdwyer/building-a-crm-app-with-nodejs-repl-it-and-mongodb-119r72mczg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the challenges I found were (trigger warning, generalisations):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writers and other people who are closer to ‘artists’ than ‘technicians’ will complain about people wanting to “pay in exposure”, but they also are more attached to the ownership of their work and they do &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; exposure. Coders are very happy to write a fixed amount of code, sell it, and move on, leaving the client to own, re-sell, rework, or publish the code as they see fit. With writers, what happens to the intellectual property gets more complicated. For example, publishing the work under my codementor profile is necessary as I have a following on CodeMentor which is part of what makes the post valuable to the client, but it also makes it look like I am committing some kind of intellectual fraud by ‘stealing’ another writer’s work. I am still not sure exactly how to handle this aspect, but I hope that once enough people (instead of just 2) have worked on a single article, the feeling of ‘ownership’ will become more diluted and this will be less of an issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s very hard to find technical writers. While the advert I posted got some strong responses, people were usually stronger either at coding or at writing, but few people had broad technical experience and were good at writing (both in terms of basic good sentence construction and more subtly being proficient at explaining technical concepts in a simple way).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding more people (writers, editors, quality checkers, designers) adds a lot of inefficiency and communication overhead. Even finding a common platform to communicate (Slack, Email, WhatsApp, Google Docs, etc) was tricky. I think there is a strong element of ‘it gets worse before it gets better’ at play, as building the pipeline is difficult, but once everyone is used to the system, it should be much easier than having one person try to tackle all aspects of producing a high quality article.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While adding more people can raise quality, it can also lower it. No one really feels the ownership that drives many informal technical writers towards perfection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are others, but overall it was a successful experiment and I was happy that the proof of concept worked out. In 2020, I hope to define some of the ideas in the pitches above a bit more closely and spend more time looking at the demand side of the market &amp;ndash; are there companies out there who are willing to pay premiums for high quality content. My back of the envelope calculations and some slight market research tells me that I should aim for around $1/word, but this is higher than I have charged before and I am still exploring how large the market for this kind of work might be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;moving-to-europe-and-applying-for-visas&#34;&gt;Moving to Europe and applying for visas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to move to Europe this year and spent countless hours looking at how to do this while maintaining &lt;em&gt;autonomy&lt;/em&gt;. The traditional route is to get a job or get married, but I find the idea of my country of residence being tied to either my employer or my partner to be very unsettling. The main alternatives that I looked into are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Netherlands&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Dutch ‘orientation’ visa. This is a visa that allows people who have studied in the Netherlands to live there commitment-free for one year, while they look for a job or work towards one of the other Dutch visas. Luckily I was eligible for this and this was the one I ended up applying for and getting. It is valid until August 2020 which is coming up fast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Dutch ‘freelance’ visa. This allows you to be self-employed but you have to go through a rigorous process to prove that you can sustain yourself and that you have clients in NL. If I had spent the 12 months from the Orientation Visa focusing on building a client base in NL, I think this could have worked well for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Dutch ‘startup’ visa. This also allows you to stay in NL without traditional employment, but the application process is even more onerous than the freelancer one, and requires you to be part of a recognised incubator, most of which charge up to $500/month. I looked at a few of these recognised incubators and I am in contact with a few of them, and I hope to keep this as an option for 2020.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PayRolling Services: there is apparently no shortage of companies who are willing to put you on their payroll in return for a fee (also around $500/month from what I gather, though I haven’t investigated too deeply). This allows you to freelance while looking like an employee, which makes many things easier and can also help with visas. They look exceptionally dodgy at first, but after talking to some people, including one expensive immigration lawyer, the practice seems fairly well regulated and supported by Governments, especially in NL. I would consider this as an option for 2020 too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Partnership visa: the Dutch are more liberal than most countries in Europe and allow you to get a partnership visa without being married. You have to have been in a monogamous relationship for 6 months or more with an EU national who lives in NL, and there are some onerous requirements to prove that your relationship is real and some frighteningly short timelines of what to do in the case of a break-up, but this is a step forward from requiring marriage. We briefly looked at this option before Isabel decided to take a job in Zurich instead of Amsterdam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;United Kingdom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The UK offers a ‘Tier 1’ visa, which offer far more more autonomy than ‘Tier 2’ visas. It is called the “Exceptional Talent” visa and is for high achievers in fields of science &amp;amp; medicine, engineering, humanities, digital technology, and arts &amp;amp; culture. I was very happy to discover this option as I thought I met all of the requirements (including being in a leadership position in digital technology, being able to demonstrate that you are helping push technological research, being a lifelong learner, and contributing to technology communities), and it offered a good deal of autonomy (no requirements to spend time in the UK, remain with a specific employer, remain employed, and a fast track option to permanent residence) and I spent many hours on the application process, putting together countless documents and ‘evidence’ and also significantly inconveniencing three people I had previously worked with for recommendation letters that had to follow very specific guidelines. I was fairly optimistic, but received a very definite and harsh rejection, which was a good reality check for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Switzerland&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some cantons in Switzerland, including Zurich, also offer a ‘partnership’ visa (amusingly called the ‘concubine visa’) which allows residence with a partner without being married. I have just submitted an application for one of these and hope to hear a response in a few weeks. As it is not a national visa, there is very little official information on it, but I by chance met someone who had gotten one, and shortly afterwards met someone else who also had one. Between the information they shared, information from some internet forums, and some information from the migrational office, we managed to piece together most of the requirements. In Zurich (much stricter than Basel), these include a relationship of at least 3 years, proof of financial stability, language proficiency, and more. I printed out nearly 100 pages in the end to hand to the embassy, and we expect them to still request more documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Switzerland also offers a startup visa, but it looks like it is exceptionally rare and difficult to get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Germany&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Germany also offers a freelance visa, with slightly more lenient requirements than NL. I have not looked too deeply into this one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I applied for 7 visas/permits this year (including an SA passport renewal, which was the worst experience of the lot). I received 4, got rejected for one, and am still awaiting a response from the last one. These are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The orientation year visa for the NL (received)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An MVV for the NL (a short visa required to collect the residence permit) (received)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Schengen Visa for Switzerland (received)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A partnership visa for Switzerland (submitted)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Tier 1 ‘exceptional talent’ visa for the UK (rejected, under appeal)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A general visitor visa for the UK (received)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not track the visa fees, travel costs and sundry expenses (not to mention the hours spent and frustrations caused) from all of these applications, but it definitely comes to far more than seems fair considering all I want to do is walk on different pieces of our globe and talk to and work with people from different countries and cultures. Which connects nicely to my next topic: anarchism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;book-highlights-from-2019&#34;&gt;Book highlights from 2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, I read mainly non-fiction and for the first time started sampling the ‘business’ and ‘management’ sections of bookshops. I continued reading some titles from these sections and continued finding them to be 90% bullshit, but I’ll put it down to a guilty pleasure for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also started exploring some other areas, mainly in finance, economics and politics. The highlights were&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noam Chomsky. I read the whole of ‘How the World Works’ and several sections of half a dozen or so of his other books. There is a lot of repetition, but I was surprised to learn more about Anarchism and how the common-usage of the term has polluted the political theory, which is very different from the ‘chaos’ definition. ‘&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oB9rp_SAp2U&#34;&gt;What is Anarchism&lt;/a&gt;’ is a great video introduction. I had mainly come across Chomsky for his work in Computer Science, and somewhat in Linguistics before, but had never engaged with his political works. I found the fact that he can be so knowledgeable about all three fields to be inspiring and many of his reports about the actions by the US government and big corporations to be eye-opening. Noam Chomsky also talks a lot about ‘wage slaves’ and about how the fact that we have come to accept the requirement of working 40 hours a week for 50+ years is recent and far from natural, which ties very well into some of the concepts I had started developing under the ‘ritza’ umbrella.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Bull-History-Boom-Bust-1982-2004/dp/0060564148&#34;&gt;Bull! A history of the boom and the bust&lt;/a&gt;. A long read and definitely not a page turner, but it was interesting to see more context, history, detail, and nuance in “we’re in a tech bubble”; “no we’re not” debate that I see almost daily on the internet. I’m still ‘team bubble’, but I have been since 2014 when I first started understanding how markets work, and I’m very aware that there is no credit in calling a bubble every year until it happens. I also read &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Too-Big-Fail-Washington-System/dp/0143118242&#34;&gt;Too Big To Fail&lt;/a&gt; and a few other books about finance and US banking that go into more depth than the Michael Lewis books I had read before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made decent progress in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/People-Power-Profits-Progressive-Capitalism/dp/1324004215&#34;&gt;People, Power, and Profits&lt;/a&gt;, but found it fairly repetitive, and dropped it around 60% of the way through. Until recently I rarely left a book unfinished if I made it past one chapter, but I have recently read more about the idea that each book primarily teaches you one new concept or framework, and it’s often not necessary to read the entire book in order to get 80% of the benefit from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read most of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Skin-Game-Hidden-Asymmetries-Daily/dp/042528462X&#34;&gt;Skin in the Game&lt;/a&gt;, but found it very inferior compared to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Fooled-Randomness-Hidden-Markets-Incerto/dp/0812975219&#34;&gt;Fooled by Randomness&lt;/a&gt;, which for me is still the best book by Taleb, and has the least condescension and obvious arrogance, but instead more hard details about interesting ideas. I might be biased though as I have a soft spot for probability, having come across it several times while studying mathematics, computer science, and philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Bad-Blood-Secrets-Silicon-Startup/dp/152473165X&#34;&gt;Bad Blood&lt;/a&gt;, and strongly believe that we will see many similar stories in 2020 as the cheap glitter starts to fall off some of the largest tech startups and unicorns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;inspirations&#34;&gt;Inspirations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continue to be inspired by the ‘maker’ crowd online. Although the bullshit in this space is noticeably growing with its profitability, there is still a very good signal:noise ratio in the community overall, and some inspirational figures such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pieter Levels &lt;a href=&#34;https://levels.io/&#34;&gt;https://levels.io/&lt;/a&gt; who started NomadList and various other highly popular services single handedly. I finally bought a lifetime subscription while it was on special, and although the community isn’t as good as I was hoping (filled with people trying to make a quick buck, and run off a free slack channel where the lack of message history is frustrating), I have made one or two good connections through there, and it is a good place to meet people on short notice while travelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://themakingof.carrd.co/&#34;&gt;AJ&lt;/a&gt; from carrd.co &amp;ndash; another service that I have admired for many years and finally opened my wallet to this year. I used the premium version of Carrd to create &lt;a href=&#34;https://flaskbyexample.com/&#34;&gt;https://flaskbyexample.com/&lt;/a&gt; for my book, &lt;a href=&#34;https://conceptconcerts.co.za/&#34;&gt;https://conceptconcerts.co.za/&lt;/a&gt; for my sister’s classical music company, &lt;a href=&#34;https://startyourown.co/&#34;&gt;https://startyourown.co/&lt;/a&gt; for a project I started at the beginning of the year but dropped, and a few others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cory Zue (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coryzue.com/&#34;&gt;http://www.coryzue.com/&lt;/a&gt;) who I met in Cape Town and had some very good conversations with. I have been following his posts closely and his humbleness and openness along with the fact that he is actually executing and not just talking continues to inspire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m already a month behind because I have been on the road (well train tracks) since January the 1st and only got back home yesterday, but here’s to reading this in 11 months’ time and cringing slightly!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Process</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/process/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 06:28:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/process/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Process is designed to make systems more efficient, but it often slows them down. The real purpose of process is to make systems, and especially employees, more &lt;em&gt;fungible&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are lucky enough to work with a small group of intelligent people, dedicated to a single cause, process is probably hurting them more than helping them. You should remove it. Nearly all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No Code</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/no-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2019 11:02:16 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/no-code/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pieter Levels, the guy behind NomadList and RemoteOK, and bunch of other interesting ideas wrote a short post earlier today about the future of building applications without code. It is at &lt;a href=&#34;https://levels.io/no-code/&#34;&gt;https://levels.io/no-code/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree with most of the ideas, including&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s getting easier to build applications that can solve complex problems and generate value, without writing code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More companies will do this over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re still far off from finding a more efficient way to build &lt;em&gt;complicated&lt;/em&gt; applications than &amp;lsquo;manually&amp;rsquo; stiching if statement and while loops together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People have been claiming better ways to write code for decades, and although we&amp;rsquo;ve seen a lot of advances, we&amp;rsquo;re still essentially writing if statements and loops, and therefore it&amp;rsquo;s reasonable to bet on the fact that this is going to continue for quite some time (see the &amp;ldquo;Lindy effect&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not completely behind the core prediction that Pieter makes though, namely&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we&amp;rsquo;ll see coding go in two directions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;towards simplicity with no code, for 95-99% of apps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;towards complexity with custom high-level engineered code, for the 1-5% of apps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The engineers working on (2) will be high paid, in the millions/year, because custom code&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The argument of &amp;ldquo;people will get paid millions for doing something highly specialist&amp;rdquo; is always going to hold true in some form, but in the case of engineering this will also be offset somewhat by the fact that millions of people are currently training to write code, and if the world moves towards needing less code, the laws of supply and demand suggest that even specialists will start to be paid &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; not &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; to write the highly custom code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As coding becomes more accessible there will be more and ore emphasis on &lt;em&gt;tooling&lt;/em&gt;. We are already seeing this a lot in the JavaScript and DevOps world - an oversupply of different tools, very few people who know which ones to use and how to use them together efficiently, and a big mess of people exaggarating the capabilities of these tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the world can go several ways from here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The demand for technology continues to grow, and even with more coding bootcamps and other &amp;lsquo;shortcuts&amp;rsquo; to produce software developers, the supply can&amp;rsquo;t keep up. Coders get paid more for having less expertise, and it becomes easier and easier to make a decent living from learning basic technology for at least another generation or two, until these skills are recognised as so vital that they are taught in schools, and we fix the &amp;lsquo;tech skills gap&amp;rsquo;. This seems unlikely to me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The demand for technology continues to grow, but we find a way to scale it without human expertise. It is now possible for a single person to build an application consisting of web servers, databases, frontend and backend code, API integrations, and more. Before it would have taken teams of sysadmins to handle the hardware, DBAs to manage the databases, software developers to write the code. And yet in spite of this supposed reduction in need, we don&amp;rsquo;t see massive job losses in technology - most people who have already specialised in one area can move to other areas as Sysadmin/DBAing becomes less in demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Survivorship bias through annoying &#39;success stores&#39;</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/lucky-success-stories/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 13:19:38 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/lucky-success-stories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most people who are successful acknowledge the role that luck plays. Some people don&amp;rsquo;t. I&amp;rsquo;m going to assume that there is &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; element of luck - 100 businesses may be nearly identical in all aspects generally regarded to be likely to affect the success of the business. One of them might do very well for no easily discernable reason, while the others fall into obscurity or disappear altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one who is successful will probably write a story telling the world how they achieved success. Some times the story is compelling and useful. Sometimes you&amp;rsquo;ll hear about the specific challenges, specific things that they tried. What worked, what didn&amp;rsquo;t, and why they think this was the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many other cases, you&amp;rsquo;ll hear a bunch of super generic advice, like &amp;lsquo;be authentic and vulnerable&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find this disproportionally irritating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure the person who wrote &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.indiehackers.com/post/705e5f895b&#34;&gt;this post on indiehackers&lt;/a&gt; is a great person. He is probably more persistent, more intelligent, harder working, and more knowledgeable than I am. He probably wins in authenticity and vulnerability too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I still find the post generally bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem well thought out. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem like he specifically picked those 5 points from a bunch of candidates. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel like he has thought about any of the points for more than a few minutes. He doesn&amp;rsquo;t talk in detail about what he tried that didn&amp;rsquo;t work, about what &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to focus on. He doesn&amp;rsquo;t really say much that is interesting at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why are &amp;ldquo;time your posts&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;be vulnerable&amp;rdquo; in the same list of 5 points. Are these the most important 5 things you can do? Are these the first 5 things he thought about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is he the lucky 1-in-100 person who happened to reach the tipping point in a couple of posts and become semi-well-known for not doing too much? Are there people with better products who tried harder, did better, were better, but were unlucky?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It kind of feels like it. But we don&amp;rsquo;t hear about them, so we can&amp;rsquo;t know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I signed up for the service anyway because it looks pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overcoming Self Refuting Statements</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/overcoming-self-refuting-statements/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2019 08:05:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/overcoming-self-refuting-statements/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A self-refuting statement is a statement that logically proves itself false. Philosophers and logicians have been arguing about exactly &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-refuting_idea&#34;&gt;what this means&lt;/a&gt; for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I&amp;rsquo;m going work from a broader definition of &lt;em&gt;a statement that&amp;rsquo;s mere existence makes the reader immediately assume that the opposite is true&lt;/em&gt;. For example, &amp;ldquo;This is not a pyramid scheme&amp;rdquo; is a phrase usually only used during the attempt to get someone to buy into a pyramid scheme (or now, more often in comedy too). Another example is &amp;ldquo;This is not a self-help book&amp;rdquo;, which is a phrase that seems to be near to becoming both necessary and sufficient to define the surrounding materials as a self help book. A final one that might be close to home for software engineers &amp;ldquo;I am not like the other recruiters&amp;rdquo;, a phrase used by a group of people who are very much like each other, but get better results by distancing themselves from their (often awful) peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming that in any field there are less-than-perfectly-honest people trying to profit from that field by peddling snake oil as something valuable while advocating the virtue of their oil by repeatedly claiming that it is not snake oil, we will usually have a (far smaller) group of people who &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; different. People whose thoughts are made only of the purest goodness and authenticity, people who don&amp;rsquo;t care about profit or politics, and who would never take advantage of another soul for personal gain. These people &lt;em&gt;create&lt;/em&gt; value instead of &lt;em&gt;extracting&lt;/em&gt; value, but from the outside they look identical to the value extractors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s imagine we have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A customer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A snake-oil peddler&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A value creator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is in the common interests of the customer and the value creator to be able to distinguish between the value creator and the snake-oil peddler, but there is no way to tell them apart. Both the snake-oil peddler and the value creator knock on the customer&amp;rsquo;s door at the same time and when he answers, they alternately state in increasingly louder voices &amp;ldquo;I am not a snake-oil peddler. I am different from the others&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a frustrating experience for everyone involved and the customer slams the door. The value creator gives up and goes home. The snake-oil peddler continues going from door to door, having more success now that there is less competition, and he finds it easier to deal with the door-slamming as on some deeply hidden ethical level he feels he kind of deserves it, while the value creator feels hurt and frustrated by the level of injustice that the universe has tossed his way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The value creator has an idea: he writes an article and posts it online for the whole world to read, describing his experience. &lt;em&gt;Now&lt;/em&gt; they&amp;rsquo;ll know that he is the true value creator, and when a customer asks &amp;ldquo;how do I know you&amp;rsquo;re not a snake-oil peddler&amp;rdquo;, he&amp;rsquo;ll point them to the article and say &amp;ldquo;look, would a snake-oil peddler write all of that?&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The value creator has won. He has gained value, and no-one has lost any. No one has been scammed. Soon the snake-oil peddlers will be but a distant unpleasant memory. He falls asleep, happy with his solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next morning he wakes up and sees his article has done well. Too well. All of the snake-oil peddlers have already written their own version saying more or less the same thing, but point themselves out as value creators &amp;ndash; and again no one can tell the value creator and snake-oil peddlers apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The value creator briefly considers writing another article, one meta-level higher, but quickly realises that this is a futile direction. There are too many of them and they are too good at immitating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is only then that the value creator realises that only a snake-oil peddler would ever use a phrase like &amp;ldquo;value creator&amp;rdquo; anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bets</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/bets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 09:21:33 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/bets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I disagree with people about things. Sometimes I am right, sometimes I am wrong, and sometimes the disagreement is about something that cannot be proven either way for many years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a list of some of those things, for the record and for fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;remote-working&#34;&gt;Remote working&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remote working will become far more normal in most industries. Currently, people are flocking to cities and hubs in unsustainable ways. They pay a huge amount of rent for a tiny apartment, and leave it empty most of the day. They go to a very expensive office to sit in a cramped and distracting environment, where they get very little done, and get sick a lot more than people who do not do this. All of these things are liabilities, to people and to companies, and companies that work out how to still produce as much value, but who do so in places where office and home rentals are far lower, and who therefore can pay their employees less, and have them be happier and healthier, are likely to &amp;ldquo;win out&amp;rdquo; over their competitors. There are many other advantages, such as being able to hire from a far larger talent pool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies that are doing this now (GitLab, Buffer, etc &amp;ndash; see &lt;a href=&#34;http://remoteonly.org/&#34;&gt;RemoteOnly.org&lt;/a&gt;) will have a competitive advantage. Working in a distributed environment is very different from working in a colocated one, and it takes practice, both to manage and to particpate in. People who have exprience leading or working in remote teams will be in demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within 5 years from today, 80% of companies in the S&amp;amp;P 500 &lt;em&gt;that have been formed in the previous 20 years&lt;/em&gt; will be employing at least 20% of their staff into fully remote roles. Older, more conservative companies, will be trying to catch up and add processes that allow for this too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;stock-market-correction--tech-bubble-burst&#34;&gt;Stock market correction / tech bubble burst&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within 3 years from today we will see another stock market event which is similar to the 2001 and 2008 crashes. People will realise that businesses like Uber and WeWork are not sustainable, and that nothing actually changed after these previous crashes (except there being potentially &amp;ldquo;further to fall&amp;rdquo;. Profit will become a more important metric than Growth. Sustainability will become more important than Growth. Venture capital will become less common. Bootstrapping will become more common. Smaller companies making the kind of headline news currently reserved for FAANG companies will become more common.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;marketing-ideas-will-change&#34;&gt;Marketing ideas will change&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Targeted advertising will become heavily regulated within the next 5 years, and it will be less profitable. Digital agencies that focus only only PPC adverts and similar will go out of business or have to restructure fast. Content marketing will become the focus of online marketing. This will be two-pronged - marketing people will target:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learners: people scouring the internet to educate themselves. There will be high quality, free, educational material that also positions products and services to the consumer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Entertainment seekers: people randomly wading through the internet looking to pass the time by watching random videos will see higher quality entertainment, which includes product placement and similar tactics to make sure that the marketing and entertainment are so closely integrated that the marketing can not be blocked out or removed, leaving only the entertainment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tba&#34;&gt;TBA&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This list will be updated along with dates of when specific updates were made.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paradoxes in Marketing</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/paradoxes-in-marketing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 08:50:37 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/paradoxes-in-marketing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, aiming at a goal is the best way to ensure that you hit that goal. At other times, the relationship is more subtle (for example, what you &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; might be goal, could actualy &lt;a href=&#34;../measurements-as-goals&#34;&gt;be a measurement&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cases, aiming at the goal, or at least what seems to be the goal, is surest way to &lt;em&gt;miss&lt;/em&gt; the goal. Take, for example, the fairly modern fad of &amp;ldquo;networking&amp;rdquo;. The basic idea is that &amp;ldquo;networks&amp;rdquo; are valuable &amp;ndash; you don&amp;rsquo;t know exactly which of your connections will help you in what way or at what time, but it is very common for &lt;em&gt;somone&lt;/em&gt; that you know to provide you with &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, the larger your &amp;ldquo;network&amp;rdquo; is, the more likely you are to be able to extract value from it &amp;ndash; exactly what value and exactly when is not possible to know, but you know that it will happen &lt;em&gt;at some point&lt;/em&gt;, and that is valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, most people want to grow their &amp;ldquo;networks&amp;rdquo; so that they can extract more value from them. They go to &amp;ldquo;networking&amp;rdquo; events, looking to meet people who might be valuable to them and add them to their network. Everyone else at the event is doing the same, and therefore few &amp;ldquo;matches&amp;rdquo; are made (two people trying to extract value from each other barely ever form a symbiotic relationship).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only way to extract value from networking events is to force yourself to completely forget that that is the goal. If you can &lt;em&gt;provide&lt;/em&gt; value to the network, people will flock to you, remember you, and potentially provide value back at some point in the future. Of course, you can see this as simply still &amp;ldquo;extracting value&amp;rdquo;, just in a cleverer way. An economist might say that you are &amp;ldquo;growing the pie&amp;rdquo; instead of &amp;ldquo;taking value from the pie&amp;rdquo;. But people look at &lt;em&gt;providing&lt;/em&gt; value for all sorts of reasons &amp;ndash; maybe even because they enjoy doing so. Those people are usually the most successful at eventually seeing the value returned. Even if you act as though you are focussed on providing value, but are actually looking to extract value using value creation as a tactic, you will be distracted from providing true value. Your focus will be on the measurement (value extraction) rather than the goal (providing value), and you will create less value, and therefore extract less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is related to marketing. Your marketing efforts should be focussed on helping your potential customers in any possible way. This could involve pointing them to your competitors (if it looks like a competitor might actually be a better choice for their specific needs), it could involve educating them about things that they want to know more about, and it almost certainly involves positioning yourself in a trustworthy way, rather than in a &amp;ldquo;I am here to try to convince you that my product is the best, using any tactics necessary&amp;rdquo; way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forget about the goal of getting the user to discover your product, and focus on giving value to the user, and the user is more likely to discover your product.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solutions Without Problems</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/solutions-without-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2019 22:09:20 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/solutions-without-problems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many people have problems without solution. This can be frustrating for those people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s more and more common for people to have solutions without problems, which can also be frustrating for those people, and for those around them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially in over-hyped spaces, such as big data, blockchain, deep learning, data science, and the internet of things, people look for problems that they can solve. This is almost always misguided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who want to &amp;ldquo;do data science&amp;rdquo; usually don&amp;rsquo;t. That is, they usually both don&amp;rsquo;t actually &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to do data science, once they realise what it is, and they usually don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; data science while they are working out what it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are going to spend hours of your life cleaning and understanding a data set, you usually have to either a) be getting paid a lot of money, or b) care deeply about the problem that you are analysing. The problem could be many things, from how to optimize a sales process, to how quickly the environment is being destroyed, but the problem &lt;em&gt;definitely isn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; that no one was &amp;ldquo;doing data science&amp;rdquo; before, and now someone is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People often say to me things like &amp;ldquo;I want to learn Django - what is a good way of doing this?&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s usually easiest to learn $thing when you have a problem and $thing is a solution. It&amp;rsquo;s more difficult to learn $thing, when $thing is designed to solve a problem that you don&amp;rsquo;t have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teachers make this mistake too. They tell their students to learn webpack, or bootstrap, or Object Oriented Programming, or databases. And they show their students how these solutions work. But often they don&amp;rsquo;t make sure that their students understand the problems that these solutions aim to solve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to understand a problem is to encounter it. It is possible to understand a problem in a more theoretical way, by talking to someone who encountered the problem, or talking to someone who spoke to someone who encountered the problem, but the further removed you are from experiencing a problem first hand, the more difficult it is to understand the subtleties or to see the need for the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for solutions to problems you have, rather than problems for the solutions you have.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measurements are not Goals</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/measurements-as-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 10:51:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/measurements-as-goals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goodhart%27s_law&#34;&gt;Charles Goodhart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measuring stuff is generally useful. Data, in general, is useful too. If you&amp;rsquo;re trying to run a big complicated business, it&amp;rsquo;s definitely a good idea to look at data, see what works, what doesn&amp;rsquo;t, and make decisions accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measurements should never be goals. Ever. Maybe the number of lines of code your programmers are writing is in some way linked to their value as a programmer, but paying or promoting them based on LoC is an obviously &lt;em&gt;terrible&lt;/em&gt; idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the number of page views your content writers get for your blog is somehow linked to their value as content writers, but asking them to produce articles that get more page views is also a terrible idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the amount of revenue your sales team generates is indicative of how well your business is doing overall, but incentivising them to make sales at any cost is a terrible idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell people your goals, and talk about how you can reach the goal together, and use measurements to see how well you are doing. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing wrong with measurements, until you spend more time looking at the measurements than the goal. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to become so invested in the measurements that you forget completely what your goal originally was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measurements are far more visible, far easier to game, and far more addictive than goals. They can be useful, but be wary of them and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cobra_effect&#34;&gt;unintended consequences&lt;/a&gt; that they can produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to tell the difference between measurements and goals. Usually, you start with a goal and develop the measurements afterwards, but some measurements are now so entrenched that they seem like goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps controversially, all of the following are usually measurements, not goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revenue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Profit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conversion rates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lines of code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test coverage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page views&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number of sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Churn rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number of tickets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And many more. And yet you&amp;rsquo;ll probably see them listed as goals in meetings, OKRs, KPIs, job descriptions, score cards. Aiming at any of the above is a great way to improve any of the above, at the expense of the goal that you may or may not have explicitly defined somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many businesses look at measurements daily or weekly, and goals quarterly or yearly. Maybe everyone would be better off and happier if these were reversed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gaming Seo</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/gaming-seo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 15:13:48 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/gaming-seo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is no shortage of people, agencies, books, and videos out there that will teach you how to game Google&amp;rsquo;s algorithms and get your content onto page one. You&amp;rsquo;ll learn how to &amp;ldquo;rank for specific keywords&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;optimise your content strategy&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;increase your domain authority&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;get 5000% returns, GUARANTEED from this AMAZING course FREE FOR TODAY ONLY!!!&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Search Engine Optimisation or SEO isn&amp;rsquo;t all bullshit, but the ratio of bullshit to reasonable ideas is around 9:1 in my experience. And the 10% of content that is authentically attempting to help people through education is largely common sense - write content that people want to read, make sure your page loads fast and all devices, use sane page structures that Google can easily understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strategy that works remarkable well but which most people won&amp;rsquo;t tell you about, because it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to charge money for, is to leave search engine optimization to search engines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google spends unthinkable amounts of money in trying to make their main product — Google search — as useful as possible. They are attempting to optimize their search engine to show people relevant content. And they&amp;rsquo;re pretty good at it. Trying to optimize your content for search engines is certainly possible, but it&amp;rsquo;s an ever-changing game which takes a lot of time, effort, and money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a choice between spending $10k of your hard-earned and 100 hours of your increasingly rare time on drawing visitors to your website, you have to divide it among the following areas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing content that people want to read or finding and paying good content writers who write content that people want to read&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Strategizing&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Brainstorming&amp;rdquo; about topic ideas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buying SEO software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paying SEO specialists to do any of the above&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paying software developers to optimize the speed of your site through caching, CDNs, deferred JavaScript and any other number of tricks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buying training courses and books for yourself and your team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doing ritualistic animal sacrifices to the SEO Gods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of them are likely to help in some way, and you can combine in anyway that you think will work for you,  but focussing only on &lt;em&gt;1.&lt;/em&gt; has a few advantages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantage one&lt;/strong&gt;: It&amp;rsquo;s not complicated. Write content that &lt;em&gt;educates&lt;/em&gt; your potential customers for free, and they&amp;rsquo;ll love it. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about which SEO methods really work and which are snake oil. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to ask if the software is really worth that insane monthly price tag. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to wonder if that Expert is really Expert or if he is in fact a Non-Expert-Pretending-To-Be-An-Expert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantage two&lt;/strong&gt;: You leave SEO to Google, who are definitely fairly good at it. They&amp;rsquo;ll make sure that changes to their algorithms still return content like yours, instead of vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantage three:&lt;/strong&gt; You&amp;rsquo;ll be making the internet, and therefore the world, a better place by creating content that people want to read instead of creating yet another clickbait piece that somehow generates a small amount of money for you for a short time and a huge amount of money for Google when combined with all the other similar content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the easy way out is the best. Write good content that helps solve real problems that people have and Google will help people find it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Give Advice</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/give-advice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 21:37:59 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/give-advice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid to give advice to strangers online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To (probably) misquote Douglas Adams:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asking people about their opinions is a great way of making friends. Telling people about your opinions can also work, but normally not quite as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And he definitely wasn&amp;rsquo;t wrong. Similar to opinions, asking people for advice is a good way of making friends too. Giving people unrequested advice is a good way to annoy them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are many people online who have experiences, fight problems, and win. They realise that they only won because they sifted through thousands of pages of advice from random strangers online, and they want to be part of that system. They want to help others sift through the outdated and irrelevant content more quickly, show people where they went wrong, and help them reach a solution more quickly. This is a common pattern for technical problems (&amp;ldquo;how I got this obscure binary to run on Haiku&amp;rdquo;) and less-technical problems (&amp;ldquo;how I realised that programming was more about building systems than writing if statements and then realised that building systems was more about talking to people than writing code&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technical or less technical, people want to blog, and then they realise that writing is hard. They write down some advice on how to solve a problem, and then they wonder if it&amp;rsquo;s actually good advice or not. What if it&amp;rsquo;s bad advice? What if they&amp;rsquo;re just adding to the problem of &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/386/&#34;&gt;people being wrong on the internet&lt;/a&gt;. So they fall into a safer mode of starting every paragraph with &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo; and describing what happened to them. That can&amp;rsquo;t be wrong right? And they avoid becoming one of those annoying know-it-alls if they&amp;rsquo;re not actually giving advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But writing words on the internet is different from talking to someone. Giving advice when people don&amp;rsquo;t ask for it is frowned upon because it&amp;rsquo;s a lot harder for someone you&amp;rsquo;re talking to to say &amp;ldquo;I get that you have good intentions, but I don&amp;rsquo;t actually respect you and your advice isn&amp;rsquo;t super relevant to me right now&amp;rdquo; than it is for someone to close a browser tab that they opened by mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So go out and there and throw your advice into the huge pit. Before you publish, check how often you use the word &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo;. If it&amp;rsquo;s a lot, and your main intention is to help other people, try to rewrite the post without using the word &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your blog has a comments section, people might tell you that you&amp;rsquo;re wrong (and then you might &lt;a href=&#34;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Cunningham%27s_Law&#34;&gt;learn something&lt;/a&gt;. More likely, you&amp;rsquo;ll get ignored. Maybe someone will &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sixhobbits&#34;&gt;tweet at you&lt;/a&gt; and tell you that thing you wrote about helped them. That always feels nice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 Retrospective</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2018-retrospective/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 17:20:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2018-retrospective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a (late) 2018 retrospective. It&amp;rsquo;s mainly for personal use as I enjoy looking back and seeing how naive I was $n$ years ago, but I&amp;rsquo;ve enjoyed reading retrospectives from others in the tech community so I&amp;rsquo;m making it public without advertising it too widely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-year-of-employment&#34;&gt;The year of employment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took up full time employment at CoGrammar (formerly HyperionDev, a product we still run) in November 2017. As I&amp;rsquo;m still here, 2018 marks my first year ever of uninterrupted full time employment (I previously did two relatively long periods at AWS, but these were interleved between academic commitments). I enjoyed my time at AWS, but I found the days got repetitive, and I disliked the feeling of being a small ant in someone&amp;rsquo;s machine, especially the processes around performance reviews and having to display an employer-issued ID card.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joining a startup proved an OK soltion to my concerns about being an employee. No ID cards, no repetition, no end of learning experiences, and very few broken processes or misguided authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went into CoGrammar as a typical software engineer and computer scientist. In my perspective, sales, marketing, and management were all very negative and mainly unnecessary things. My perspectives haven&amp;rsquo;t swung completely in the opposite direction, but I think they&amp;rsquo;ve become more nuanced. &lt;em&gt;Some&lt;/em&gt; sales and marketing can be bucketed under information sharing; sales and marketing are far more valuable to most businesses than technology; and management, in some cases, really can be about productivity multiplying and mentoring rather than being focussed on hot air production and politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest change for me was moving into a leadership role where I needed to spend more time talking to people and less and less time writing code. In 2014, I was terrified of making phone calls, and was a firmly self-identified introvert, who preferred talking to computers than people. In 2015 I saw a bit more of Europe, and spent more time talking to people from different backgrounds (my peers during my master&amp;rsquo;s programme were people from linguistics, psychology, education, and mathematics, and from all around the world, while during bachelor&amp;rsquo;s I mainly spent time with people from computer science, philosophy and classical music, nearly all from South Africa). My ideas around introversion and extroversion were challenged and I came to see extroversion as a useful skill that could be learned instead of an inherent characteristic. In general, I lived more outside my comfort zone than usual, and realised that none of the things I tended to avoid were going to kill me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I joined CoGrammar, I had some steep learning curves for a while, and it was the first time in my life where I didn&amp;rsquo;t have mentors and teachers to explicitly learn from, but instead had to learn by working with other people who expected me to teach them things. I also always thought of myself as indecisive (restaurant menus were always something that caused anxiety), so one of the things I found challenging was making decisions without perfect information and knowing that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have anyone to blame if I made the wrong calls (which I definitely did more than once). A major realisation was that this is a symptom that affects nearly everyone, and ignoring the feeling of doubt is a perfectly reasonable strategy to make better decisions. As with nearly everything, it gets easier with exlicit practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;exploring-new-literature-genres&#34;&gt;Exploring new literature genres&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always skipped the &amp;ldquo;business&amp;rdquo; shelf in bookshops, and felt very superior when I saw people reading books with titles like &amp;ldquo;High Output Management&amp;rdquo;. I am still overall skeptical of this section, but the 20-30 books I read over the last year that live on those same shelves (I sourced e-books instead), have definitely taught me things I didn&amp;rsquo;t know and I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have coped throughout this year without them as a walking prop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year was also the first year I started taking detailed notes about every book I read, and I found that this hugely improved my reading experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these books that I would hesitatingly recommend in spite of their titles are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High Output Management&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Andy Grove&lt;/em&gt;
This was the first book that made me think that maybe there &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be some value hidden on the business book shelves. When I&amp;rsquo;ve skimmed business books before, they&amp;rsquo;ve seemed exceptionally shallow, usually containing very sparse information (each vaguely interesting idea is given 2-3 chapters or a whole book instead of the paragraph it deserved), and built mainly around over-simplified graphs and models (why do business people like quad charts so much??).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;High Output Management&lt;/em&gt; was well-written (another surprise), and Andy puts his ideas about management across in a very human way. This book overall scored highly on number of novel and interesting ideas per chapter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was also part of a shift from focussing on creativity to focussing on process. When processes become too complicated (like getting teams of people work together, or producing any kind of art), we tend to give up trying to define them and look for &amp;ldquo;inspiration&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;creativity&amp;rdquo; instead. On the other side, we have people claiming to define them with &amp;ldquo;the 5 steps to x&amp;rdquo;, or similar over-simplified processes that show no understanding of the problem. Andy&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Everything is Process&amp;rdquo; argument is compelling though, and I found the book to present a good balance between admiting that some things were too complicated to fully define in a simple diagram, and not giving up on the idea completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not a complete convert. I still see too much harm caused by too much process and too much measurement (&amp;ldquo;When a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure&amp;rdquo;), but there&amp;rsquo;s definitely some value in exploring the chaos in an organized way instead of wandering around and getting lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Manager’s Path&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Camille Fournier&lt;/em&gt;
This one was less interesting overall, but after being thrown into the deep end of a people-focussed role and no idea how to do many things, this was a great step-by-step guide of how to not sink, including running 1:1s, mentoring, using leverage, giving feedback, and helped with many other problems and questions I had throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Founder&amp;rsquo;s Dilemmas&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Noam T. Wasserman&lt;/em&gt;
The main point of this book is to differentiate between entrepreneurs who become rich and those who become &amp;ldquo;king&amp;rdquo; (retain full control over their business). The central thesis is that if you aim for both, you&amp;rsquo;re likely to get neither, so you should choose carefully, but it has a bunch of other interesting tales and advice along the way, and gives some good insight into what makes the people who create high-growth startups tick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Innovator&amp;rsquo;s Dilemma&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Clayton M. Christensen&lt;/em&gt;
This one has actually been on my to-read list since 2014 when I joined Amazon but after another prompt this year I finally got round to reading it. It&amp;rsquo;s not exactly a page turner (unless you&amp;rsquo;re &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; into the disk drive market), but it&amp;rsquo;s a convincing outline of the paradox that in order to become and remain successful you have to innovate and take risks, but once you have achieved some success you cannot take risks any more. Amazon tackles this problem by having smaller subsidaries that take risks while the overarching company focuses on proven successes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a slightly different focus were &lt;em&gt;Drive: The Truth about what motivates us&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Punished by Rewards&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Flow&lt;/em&gt;. I think these are pretty well-known concepts these days, and I covered some of them in my post &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codementor.io/garethdwyer/enter-the-zone-fight-imposter-syndrome-and-unlock-intrinsic-motivation-kjpbpe5a5&#34;&gt;Enter the Zone, fight imposter syndrome, and unlock intrinsic motivation&lt;/a&gt;, so I won&amp;rsquo;t go into detail again, but these definitely belong on the list of 2018 books that had some effect on me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also read several of Nassim Taleb&amp;rsquo;s works. He&amp;rsquo;s controversial enough in both ideas and writing style that most people either love or hate his works. Personally, I really enjoyed and learned a lot from &amp;ldquo;Fooled by Randomness&amp;rdquo;, but disliked most of his other books. During my master&amp;rsquo;s studies in 2016/17, I studied probability theory in both Computer Science and Philosophy departments, and I believe that they each have something to learn from the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophy is known for tackling hard subjects before they become well-defined sciences, and as an academic subject it has lost a lot the respect that it used to command, perhaps because everything seems so well defined these days. But our understanding of probability theory is far from as stable as most scientists would have you believe. Taleb is the closest I&amp;rsquo;ve seen to a bridge between the two groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More specific to the software development industry, I also read &lt;strong&gt;The Phoenix Project&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Gene Kim, George Spafford&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Kevin Behr&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;The Mythical Man Month&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Fred Brooks&lt;/em&gt;. Both of these are easy to read and contain entertaining parables of how to scale software development. I recognised many of the problems described and successfully used some of the suggested approaches, albeit at a far smaller scale than that described in the books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hiring-and-&#34;&gt;Hiring and &amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning to interview people, set fair interview questions and take-home tests, make judgement calls about who was bullshitting and who knew their stuff, make tradeoffs around technical skill vs other skills, hire people, onboard people, negotiate contracts, and &amp;ndash; sadly &amp;ndash; offboard people too, have all been new experiences. I would have probably had a nervous breakdown by now without some of the books mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018 I re-evaluated many of my ideas about what constituted business bullshit and what was actually valuable, but I am still convinced that most employment structures are horribly broken and misguided, and that in 30-100 years time we will look at the current relationships between companies and employees as backwards and barbaric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bullshit remains one of the hardest things to identify and call out, especially once bullshit ideas are engrained in habit. Most people are unwilling to call out bullshit, and even those who are have a hard time identifying it, as it&amp;rsquo;s far easier to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On_Bullshit&#34;&gt;generate bullshit than to identify it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;technical-writing&#34;&gt;Technical writing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing and publishing technical tutorials and programming walkthroughs for several years, but this year I made more progress. I found more clients who wanted to pay for my writing, and saw my readership numbers increase substantially. In 2018, I hit 1000 followers and 500k total page views &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codementor.io/garethdwyer&#34;&gt;just on CodeMentor&lt;/a&gt; (a majority of my tutorials are published there, but I also have several &lt;a href=&#34;dwyer.co.za/writing.html&#34;&gt;around a few other places&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/hugoblog/codementor-stats-2018.png&#34; alt=&#34;Codementor Stats&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also increased my writing rate (you should probably also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kalzumeus.com/2006/08/14/you-can-probably-stand-to-charge-more/&#34;&gt;charge more&lt;/a&gt;), and was able to find some clients in the US that allow me to consider writing as a hobby and a reasonable side income stream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to grow a community of people interested in writing technical content this year, so please get in touch if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in collaborating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My non-best selling book &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.packtpub.com/web-development/flask-example&#34;&gt;Flask by Example&lt;/a&gt; continues to be a non-best seller, but sells enough copies to keep my longer-term goal of achieving a reasonable passive income stream alive. The biggest mistake I made with this book was using Python 2 (in 2015 it still looked like Python 2 might continue to dominate industry, and I was biased by the fact that I was working with a Python 2 codebase at AWS). There were other mistakes I made, and I would love to try update it in a second edition, but unfortuantely I haven&amp;rsquo;t received support from the publisher about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;digital-nomading&#34;&gt;Digital nomading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After living for the last few months of 2013 in the UK, Grahamstown for 2014, Cape Town for 2015, Germany for 2016, the Netherlands for 2017, and Cape Town again for 2018, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to feel at home anywhere. I visited Europe again in February/March and June/July and I learned to need less &lt;em&gt;stuff&lt;/em&gt; overall, travelling with only hand luggage for both trips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of my longer-term goal to avoid stuff, I acquired too much stuff in the year I was in Germany and had to get rid of most of it when I moved to NL. Again, after a year in NL I had too much stuff. Now after a year in Cape Town I have the same problem yet again. I&amp;rsquo;m a slow learner, but I hope that once I say my goodbyes to the things I have now and think I need but can probably live without (the espresso machine will be hard), I will try yet again to live with less junk in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passports and visas are still an issue, and needing to fill in forms and prove various things about myself just to be allowed the &amp;ldquo;privilege&amp;rdquo; of visiting other people&amp;rsquo;s countries is something that I deeply despise. I hope that we can move towards a world with fewer borders rather than more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were various Nomads and &amp;ldquo;Solopreneurs&amp;rdquo; that I followed fairly closely, including &lt;a href=&#34;levels.io&#34;&gt;Pieter Levels&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ajlkn&#34;&gt;aj&lt;/a&gt;. I really like how they write about their experiences and successes. Unfortunately there are definite signs of hype in the space now with many self-declared nomads working on products to help other people become nomads, leading to Tim Ferriss style pyramid schemes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;technology&#34;&gt;Technology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I picked up Django in 2017 and feel very comfortable with it after nearly two years of working with it. I prefer it in many ways to Flask now, though each still have their place. I used Django Rest Framework for the first time, and explored some challenges and tradeoffs around microservices and decentralisation compared to the more monolithic codebases that I have seen more of (anyone who tells you that one approach is obviously better than the other is probably trying to sell you something).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also gained experience with more of the AWS suite. The biggest learnings were around how people often over-estimate their technology needs. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen a single T2.micro EC2 instance scale to more users than I would have thought possible and seen how much can be saved through super-simple infrustructure architecture (both in outright costs, and in people time by keeping architectures incredibly simple). I understood the concepts of &amp;ldquo;Do things that don&amp;rsquo;t scale&amp;rdquo; before, but 2018 was the first year when I saw them properly in action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I improved my knowledge on a range of startup-oriented services, such as CRMs (avoid SalesForce like the plague if you ever can), Intercom, SendGrid, Google Suite, Google Analytics, Data Studio, Google Scripts, geolocation libraries, payment integrations (Stripe is as great as everyone says), and various other services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Front end development has never interested me much, but it&amp;rsquo;s been great working with a full-time front-end developer on a day-to-day basis and learning how to &lt;em&gt;coach&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;mentor&lt;/em&gt;, as together we had to explore front-end framworks, optimization, web-pack, scss, and many other things in what seems like an ever-deepening rabbit whole of wonder and terror.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered the value that bad code can produce and also seen very real examples of when bad code fails and causes more damage than the value it produced. Finding the balance between getting features out as fast as possible and making sure that your team isn&amp;rsquo;t building a towering pile of twigs that will burn to the ground is challenging, stressful, and oddly satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel like I&amp;rsquo;ve fallen behind some new advancements in technology already, but it&amp;rsquo;s hard to keep up with everything and to constantly discriminate between true advancements and passing fads. Things I wish I had used more include Docker, Kubernetes, most CI/CD tools, Go, React, &lt;a href=&#34;https://solid.mit.edu/&#34;&gt;Solid&lt;/a&gt; and IPFS. I also feel like I&amp;rsquo;m falling behind in the even faster moving world of deep learning, as I haven&amp;rsquo;t used the concepts I studied for two years much in 2018, and already most of the things that seemed exciting then look dated now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2019&#34;&gt;2019&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t to like set definite yearly goals, but this year (again) I am hoping to read, write and walk more, spend less time consuming &amp;ldquo;shallow&amp;rdquo; content like social media and short articles, and gain more autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to build a writing habit by writing every day, instead of only when I feel like it, which sounds like &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; autonomy, but taking into account that it leads to more enjoyable experiences (it&amp;rsquo;s usually fun writing once you start), and has a great deal of leverage, I think it overall leads to more autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My various side-projects tend to have a life-span of a few months at most. I would like 2019 to be the start of a side-project that lives for at least three years. More on that soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inconsistent Ethics and Voting</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/inconsistent-ethics-and-voting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2019 23:06:37 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/inconsistent-ethics-and-voting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Utilitarianism is an ethical framework that many people partially rely on. It&amp;rsquo;s the simplest form of ethics: if you want to know if some action is moral or not, just have a look at the &lt;em&gt;result&lt;/em&gt; of that action, and then decide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should you give food to a starving person? Sure, it will result in the starving person not being hungry, which is a moral result, so therefore the charity is a moral action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should you order a milkshake at a restaurant without asking them to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.change.org/p/starbucks-replace-plastic-straws-with-biodegradable-paper-straws&#34;&gt;hold the straw&lt;/a&gt;? No, because the straw might end up in an innocent turtle&amp;rsquo;s nose, which is an immoral result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other people may claim to follow virtue ethics, in which things are a bit more complicated. Or deontological ethics, which could make it harder still. Let&amp;rsquo;s ignore them for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not uncommon for people who vote in western democracies to assume a moral high ground over people who don&amp;rsquo;t vote. &amp;ldquo;If you don&amp;rsquo;t vote, you can&amp;rsquo;t complain&amp;rdquo; they say. &amp;ldquo;You as an individual have power&amp;rdquo;, they say. &amp;ldquo;Voting is a privilege&amp;rdquo; they say. &amp;ldquo;Imagine if everyone didn&amp;rsquo;t vote&amp;rdquo;, they say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They might be right, but they are also often logically inconsistent. All of the phrases above are false or irrelevant to the question of whether or not one has a moral obligation to vote. Even very rational people tend to get highly emotional about the topic of non-voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of fairly non-controversial facts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_close_election_results&#34;&gt;few&lt;/a&gt; elections are decided by a single vote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, you probably don&amp;rsquo;t have influence over thousands of people (say &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sixhobbits&#34;&gt;hi&lt;/a&gt; if you do).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, unless you enjoy playing the lottery, or you&amp;rsquo;re very actively involved in politics, the &lt;em&gt;outcome&lt;/em&gt; of you choosing to vote is the same as the &lt;em&gt;outcome&lt;/em&gt; of you choosing not to vote. The actual process of voting is generally something that people find unpleasant (standing in queues and filling out forms). So just like playing the lottery, voting is something that you might be advised to avoid (it&amp;rsquo;s only a small inconvenience/expense, but at the odds of it producing a favourable outcome, or having any influence at all, being so small, there&amp;rsquo;s an overall expected negative payoff).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, if you vote and broadly follow utilitarianism then, you probably shouldn&amp;rsquo;t assume a moral highground over non-voters. If you do want to assume this highground, you should be prepared to defend virtue ethics or deontology over utilitarianism and have some backing for your ideas that voting is an inherently moral action, or an action that inherently good people take part in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re running a country and want people to participate in a form of democracy, you should probably make it illegal to not vote (as in Australia), or be prepared for a slowly dwindling number of active voters.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incentives and Trust</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/incentives-and-trust/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 23:29:33 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/incentives-and-trust/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Incentives seem very well understood. We have a whole bunch of natural sounding ideas, such as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you reward a person for a specific behaviour, you&amp;rsquo;ll encourage more of that behaviour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you punish someone for a specific behaviour, you&amp;rsquo;ll encourage less of that behaviour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you need someone to do something that they don&amp;rsquo;t want to do, you need to monitor them to make sure that they actually do it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once you have monitored someone enough and they habitually do what they are meant to, then you have built mutual trust and you can stop the monitoring, or start monitoring randomly instead of constantly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of these kinds of ideas come from the BF Skinner, who was and is well respected for the very precise and scientific methods he used to study behaviour. The idea of applying something as clean-cut as science to something as messy as human behaviour wasn&amp;rsquo;t always obvious. And people are starting to question it again. To misquote someone, &amp;ldquo;Skinner did most of his experiments on rats and drew most of his conclusions about humans&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, Taylorism or &amp;ldquo;Scientific Management&amp;rdquo; was invented in the early 1900s . The idea of treating people like any other resource and optimising labour processes seems fairly natural now to anyone who has worked in an office with HR policies and commission structures, but this wasn&amp;rsquo;t always a common opinion. And it too is slowly being questioned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incentives are hard. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to fall into situations of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cobra_effect&#34;&gt;The Cobra Effect&lt;/a&gt; when designing them, in which the incentive actually encourages the opposite result of what was intended. Even when incentives work short term to modify other&amp;rsquo;s behaviour, longer term they can &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Punished-Rewards-Trouble-Incentive-Praise/dp/0618001816&#34;&gt;often have a negative result&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monitoring people can similarly &lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2018/04/why-monitoring-your-employees-behavior-can-backfire&#34;&gt;lead to an increase in undesired behaviour&lt;/a&gt;, as people will be motivated to beat the system, and they won&amp;rsquo;t feel bad about cheating because they&amp;rsquo;re not breaking your trust (if you&amp;rsquo;re monitoring, you&amp;rsquo;re indicating that an absence of trust).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these incentive and monitoring based strategies only &lt;em&gt;seem&lt;/em&gt; intuitive to us because we&amp;rsquo;ve been taught that they are &amp;ldquo;science&amp;rdquo;. But they are inventions, not discoveries, and the opposite strategies can be used as or more effectively to reach the same goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not rewarding people for behaviour can help them focus on intrinsic rather than extrinsic motivation. Avoiding punishing people for bad behaviour means that you don&amp;rsquo;t have to deal with resent. Not monitoring people indicates that you trust them, and people are usually very hesitant to break trust when it is offered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talk to individual people instead of resources. Look for shared goals to work towards together instead of identifying your goals and incentivising others to help you get there. Be suspicious of anyone who thinks that people should be treated as resources.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Salary</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/salary/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 18:14:26 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/salary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;salaries&#34;&gt;Salaries&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the big #TalkPay movement a couple of years ago, and the related discussion that came up as a result, I thought people were more aware of the imbalance between employer and employee when it comes to salary negotiation. But I still see a lot of people who are very happy to answer this question straight up. You shouldn&amp;rsquo;t. Never name the first number in a salary negotiation, and never give up any information about your previous salaries either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone argued about this with me today, saying that being open and transparent was a good start to any potential relationship. It&amp;rsquo;s sounds like a fair argument, but until there is openness and transparency &lt;em&gt;in both directions&lt;/em&gt;, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t hold water. If a company is willing to publish the salaries of all of their employees (and &lt;a href=&#34;https://open.buffer.com/transparent-salaries/&#34;&gt;some actually do this&lt;/a&gt;, then you can name the first number. Otherwise, in the interests of fair engagement rules, you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The long version of this is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kalzumeus.com/2012/01/23/salary-negotiation/&#34;&gt;over at Patio11&amp;rsquo;s article here&lt;/a&gt;, but it&amp;rsquo;s 7000 words which might be why some people haven&amp;rsquo;t come across those ideas yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re at an interview, remember that the person across the table from you has a huge advantage. They know what other people at the company are being paid. You don&amp;rsquo;t. They know what other people in the city are being paid. You might have some idea from friends and surveys, but they likely know more, mainly from interviewing 100s of other candidates who have happily divulged their own salaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company has a range that they&amp;rsquo;re willing to pay for the role before you walk in the door. After a few minutes of conversation, the range has narrowed. You have a range before you walk into the door. You don&amp;rsquo;t know each other&amp;rsquo;s ranges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For simplicities sake, let&amp;rsquo;s assume the minimum you&amp;rsquo;ll work for is $x$. The maximum they&amp;rsquo;re willing to pay is $y$. There&amp;rsquo;s no maximum for you (if they want to pay you $9999999999999999999 you&amp;rsquo;ll be happy); there&amp;rsquo;s no minimum for them (if you want to pay to work there, they&amp;rsquo;ll be happy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(-inf) _______(x)____(y)_____________ (inf)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;If $y &amp;lt; x$, it&amp;rsquo;s probably not going to work out, so let&amp;rsquo;s assume $y &amp;gt; x$. It could be that $y=x$, but it&amp;rsquo;s fairly unlikely. Whoever names the first number loses a bit. If they name $y$, you&amp;rsquo;ll take it and they&amp;rsquo;ll never know that you would have taken $x$. If you name $x$, they&amp;rsquo;ll offer $x$ and you&amp;rsquo;ll never know that they would have offered $y$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, one of you has to name a number first, and it&amp;rsquo;s likely that the first number won&amp;rsquo;t be accurate. If you name first, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably say &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m expecting $w$&amp;rdquo;, where $w$ is 10-20% higher than $x$. If the company goes first, they&amp;rsquo;ll probably say &amp;ldquo;we can offer $z$&amp;rdquo; where $z$ is 10-20% lower than y. This is another reason why it&amp;rsquo;s important for you to not go first. Although not always the case (and especially not always in tech), it&amp;rsquo;s likely that the company has more applicants for the role than you have offers from other companies. This means that the company is more likely to &amp;ldquo;walk away&amp;rdquo; than you. If you name a number that they don&amp;rsquo;t like, they&amp;rsquo;ll go with someone else. If you name a number that&amp;rsquo;s lower than your value, they&amp;rsquo;ll exploit you. However, if the company names a number that&amp;rsquo;s higher than you expected, that&amp;rsquo;s probably a better estimate of your true market worth. If the company names a number lower than you expected, it&amp;rsquo;s more likely that a positive conversation around &amp;ldquo;Everything else works for me, but I will need a higher figure than that&amp;rdquo; will work out for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t name the first number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Sidenote, recruiters will pretend to be &amp;ldquo;on your side&amp;rdquo; and they might even agree with everything above, but say that you can name the number to them and they won&amp;rsquo;t reveal to the company. They&amp;rsquo;ll just use it to give you advice and find companies that are a good match. They&amp;rsquo;re lying. Companies pay recruiters and recruiters are incentivised to give the company as much information as possible).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boredom</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/boredom/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2019 22:03:40 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/boredom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;People are afraid of boredom. They actively avoid having any time that is unscheduled. If they do find a brief moment of unscheduled time, they quickly focus on finding something to do (reading Twitter in the checkout queue).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boredom isn&amp;rsquo;t really a negative emotion. It&amp;rsquo;s not like fear or dread or hate or pain. And even busy-bodies like it for brief moments, as long as you call it &amp;ldquo;relaxation&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You get home from whatever chaotic thing seemed important at the time, and just do nothing for a while. It&amp;rsquo;s great. It&amp;rsquo;s what you wanted. And then you&amp;rsquo;re bored, and you turn on Netflix or argue about politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People don&amp;rsquo;t actually dislike boredom. Mainly they&amp;rsquo;re just worried that boredom will lead to more negative emotions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/lbIuWZX.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image result for existential dread&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And often it does. The unchecked mind with no explicit focus wanders off, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t always end up in the most positive of places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But boredom is still useful. If you have any overall, vague goals in life, boredom is one of the best ways of achieving them (or at least working out how to).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve hung around in offices or made friends with Managerial types at all, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably heard someone harp on about the &amp;ldquo;urgent/important&amp;rdquo; quadrant, which looks like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.developgoodhabits.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/How-to-Make-Decisions-on-What%E2%80%99s-Urgent-and-Important-min.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Image result for urgent important&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s oversimplified, but urgent means that the task needs to be done now, and important means that the task needs to be done at some (often unspecified) point in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stuff that is urgent always gets done before stuff that&amp;rsquo;s important, and it&amp;rsquo;s easy to let long-term important things fail, just because they never seemed urgent (e.g. finding time to sleep properly and not sitting all day &amp;ndash; these things are not urgent, because you could always do them tomorrow rather, but they&amp;rsquo;re important because you have to do them at some point or deal with rather unpleasant consequences).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boredom is a great stage to work on the important &lt;em&gt;not-urgent&lt;/em&gt; things. It takes some practice though, as even if you learn to not reach for your phone at the first sign of boredom, it&amp;rsquo;s likely that your next go-to will be some kind of stressful emotion about something that&amp;rsquo;s urgent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good place to find boredom is classical music concerts. They&amp;rsquo;re at least 90 minutes long, and have enough old, respectful people to make you feel bad for looking at your phone. After studying classical music for many years and never managing to not be bored during concerts, I&amp;rsquo;m still not brave enough to ask real musicians if they also get bored during concerts. I suspect that they do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guardian vs Dale Carnegie</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/guardian-vs-dale-carnegie/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2019 09:23:50 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/guardian-vs-dale-carnegie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Guardian released a new donation campaign ages ago. The messages at the bottom of each article always look something like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;![image-20190121092446395](/Users/g/Library/Application Support/typora-user-images/image-20190121092446395.png)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(their highlight).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve read any Dale Carnegie or other pop-psychology of a &amp;ldquo;self help&amp;rdquo; kind of nature, the first advice you usually hear about getting other people to do things for you. These people will tell you to make sure you focus not on &lt;em&gt;yourself&lt;/em&gt; but on the other person. Don&amp;rsquo;t tell your boss that you want a raise because you need to feed you children; tell him you want a raise because you&amp;rsquo;re adding extra value to his bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Guardian&amp;rsquo;s messaging seems backwards. They open by talking about falling advertising revenues. That&amp;rsquo;s unlikely to be a problem the reader can relate to, nevermind one that the reader has.  The Guardian &amp;ldquo;needs&amp;rdquo; your donations to stay open. In the next paragraph, they hint that open reporting has some benefit to the reader, but they avoid explicitly saying it. They ask you to make a donation, and focus on how easy it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowhere do they try to talk up the benefit of donating. They don&amp;rsquo;t claim to help you solve your problems. They don&amp;rsquo;t tell you that it&amp;rsquo;s your last chance to ensure that you have independent journalism tomorrow. They don&amp;rsquo;t tell you that your life is better with independent journalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a straightforward, slightly whiney, &amp;ldquo;we need money, please give it to us&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently it worked. I can&amp;rsquo;t find a link now, but I read a review on their strategy about a year after they started it where (IIRC) they claimed that the campaign had been far more successful than they had expected. Readers were moved by the message and donated generously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could this be &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; the advice from &lt;em&gt;How to Win Friends and Influence People&lt;/em&gt; is now so common place that people are tired of it? Perhaps readers are so used to business framing things as they think readers want to hear them, that this is something fresh and different?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re still in business, but apparently &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.outlookindia.com/website/story/the-guardian-goes-tabloid-cuts-300-jobs-is-donor-driven-business-model-sustainab/307179&#34;&gt;also cutting jobs and losing money&lt;/a&gt;, so I guess we&amp;rsquo;ll have to wait and see how good the strategy is on a longer term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s good to keep in mind that while flying in the face of conventional wisdom is often a good strategy, if it&amp;rsquo;s successful enough, it also becomes conventional wisdom itself. Similarly, many businesses become successful by being brave enough to try new things, but when they become large and successful, they are not longer flexible enough to try new things, and end up getting stuck. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Innovator%27s_Dilemma&#34;&gt;The Innovator&amp;rsquo;s Dilemma&lt;/a&gt; covers this in a lot more detail and is definitely worth a read, even if you&amp;rsquo;re not that interested in the Disk Drive industry from a couple of decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Technical Interviews</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/technical-interviews/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 13:05:27 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/technical-interviews/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many programmers don&amp;rsquo;t like the style of technical interviews given by most companies. In these &amp;ldquo;whiteboarding&amp;rdquo; interviews, you are usually given a difficult problem from computer science in which you have to produce a program that can take some input and efficiently produce some related output. Usually, to pass these interviews, you need to have a deep understanding of algorithms and data structures, including graph traversal algorithms, tree data structures (maybe even the dreaded red-black tree, which is known for being very complicated and hard to understand intuitively),  and dynamic programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People don&amp;rsquo;t like them because although these topics are usually taught at university computer science courses, very few people use any of that knowledge day-to-day. All of these &amp;ldquo;classic&amp;rdquo; problems have libraries that are far more efficient than the simplified algorithms taught in theory classes, and to do well at these questions, you usually need to memorise a whole bunch of &amp;ldquo;useless&amp;rdquo; knowledge (knowledge that you don&amp;rsquo;t need outside of a context where you are being evaluated).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some reason why technical interviewing hasn&amp;rsquo;t changed much in spite of the problems that people raise though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;most-companies-prefer-false-negatives-to-false-positives&#34;&gt;Most companies prefer false negatives to false positives&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interview tries to classify candidates into &amp;ldquo;hire&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t hire&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s usually better for companies to have a good candidate go into the &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t hire&amp;rdquo; pool than vice-versa. It&amp;rsquo;s far more costly to hire a &amp;ldquo;bad egg&amp;rdquo;, who can take a long time to get rid of, and cause damage, than it is to miss a &amp;ldquo;good egg&amp;rdquo; (there will always be more good eggs in the queue). There are a lot of &amp;ldquo;good eggs&amp;rdquo; who do badly at programming interviews &amp;ndash; they have more practical experience than theoretical experience, and they dislike memorising useless knowledge, but Google is happy to lose out on these. It&amp;rsquo;s far less common for someone to be able to write out a left-rotation for a red-black tree on a white board who is then incompetent in other areas. So white boarding isn&amp;rsquo;t directly testing the skills that companies actually want, but given their preferences of not hiring bad eggs, it&amp;rsquo;s a decent proxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;companies-value-predictability-and-loyalty&#34;&gt;Companies value predictability and loyalty&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who do well at whiteboarding are often similar in other ways too. They are good problem solvers (you can&amp;rsquo;t memorise every possible interview question, so while memorisation helps, you still need to be able to apply the concepts you memorised in slightly novel ways), and they&amp;rsquo;re pretty dedicated. They took the time and effort to get good at something that they knew they needed to be good at if they wanted to get hired. It&amp;rsquo;s not uncommon to study for 3-6 months to get past a technical interview at one of the large tech companies, and there&amp;rsquo;s enough information out here about what each company focuses on. If a candidate has taken the time and effort to work out how to do well at the interview, they probably really want to work for that specific company, which is a &amp;ldquo;green flag&amp;rdquo; for interviewers &amp;ndash; they didn&amp;rsquo;t just apply for the job as an afterthought one day. They really want it, and they&amp;rsquo;ll probably stick around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;there-arent-that-many-great-alternatives&#34;&gt;There aren&amp;rsquo;t that many great alternatives&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To really test someone, you need longer than a day to get to know them. The best interview would be bringing them into your existing team and to evaluate them over several weeks or months. It&amp;rsquo;s not unusual for startups to do this &amp;ndash; they often employ someone on a fixed-term short contract first and then convert them to full time employees after they&amp;rsquo;ve proven themselves, but this is highly impractical for a majority of applicants, who might have full time jobs somewhere else, or need to relocate across the world to join the company that gives them a job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m interviewing later today to be a part time technical interviewer for &lt;a href=&#34;karat.io&#34;&gt;karat.io&lt;/a&gt; (it&amp;rsquo;s a bit meta). They claim to solve some of these problems, but even after several years of academic computer science and several years of industry experience, I&amp;rsquo;m only about 40% sure that I can pass their technical interview.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hype</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/hype/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 19:16:43 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/hype/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;People like hype. Hype is hard to identify when it&amp;rsquo;s happening, and is easy to identify with hindsight. Hype can last for different amounts of time - anything from minutes to decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hype in the world of technology is bad. A recurring theme is people getting very excited about some new technology and spending thousands of hours learning about it, building programmes or even whole schools around it, and over-saturating the market without producing much value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gartner.com/en/research/methodologies/gartner-hype-cycle&#34;&gt;Gartner Hype Cycle&lt;/a&gt; has become something of a meme, and is fairly useful to talking about how hyped any new technology is. But like most business charts, it&amp;rsquo;s hugely over-simplified. Manager-types love reducing any problem to a single graph and trying to sound smart by claiming to have solved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cryptocurrency was and is an obvious hype. There is some value in the invention, but a majority of people were not using it for anything that made it a better solution than previous technology. &amp;ldquo;Big data&amp;rdquo; continues to be relevant, but also did not live up to the hype from around 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deep learning, Machine learning, AI, Data Science are reaching peak hype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good way to identify hype is to divide things into &lt;em&gt;problems&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;solutions&lt;/em&gt;. When people are focussing more on solutions than problems, it&amp;rsquo;s likely that the solution is hyped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, companies setting up &amp;ldquo;deep learning&amp;rdquo; teams or &amp;ldquo;big data&amp;rdquo; teams organises people around implementing a solution instead of solving problems. They get the latest and greatest algorithms and some highly paid people, and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; ask &amp;ldquo;what can technology $x$ do for us&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, hype can also be identified by seeing new terminology be invented for old solutions. For example, we&amp;rsquo;ve always had data analysts and statisticians. These people were widely regarded as stereotypically boring, along with accountants (any readers excluded of course). Now a lot of what these people do has been rebranded as &amp;ldquo;data science&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;AI&amp;rdquo;. AI had a very specific meaning until recently. It was a branch of computer science concerned with path finding algorithms and optimisation problems. Now that we spread the term around liberally, in nearly any case where a computer is being used to solve a problem, terminology has gotten a lot less precise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the Powers That Be have decided that &amp;ldquo;Data Scientist&amp;rdquo; is the sexiest job of the year. We&amp;rsquo;ve come a long way since Chandler Bing from &lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; was given a data analyst job as an example of the pinnacle of boring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s hard sometimes not to get caught up in the hype. Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s real. Some &amp;ldquo;AI&amp;rdquo; really did change the world, and some of it continues to do so. Big data has also changed how surveillance and marketing work, but most people don&amp;rsquo;t like talking about that as much now as when people claimed that it would cure cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s good to keep up with the hype and stay informed, but to spend a majority of your time learning about old knowledge rather. Because of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lindy_effect&#34;&gt;Lindy Effect&lt;/a&gt; it&amp;rsquo;s far more likely that something that has been relevant for the last 50 years will remain relevant for the next 50 years than something that was only invented yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk Calculation and Human Biases</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/risk-calculation-and-human-biases/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2019 09:08:47 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/risk-calculation-and-human-biases/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most days that you live through, you do some kind of &lt;em&gt;risk calculations&lt;/em&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;re seldom certain about anything, so we learn to estimate probabilities based on a wide range of knowledge and experiences, and hope for the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us humans get pretty good at this, and we use this risk calculation skill to stay alive, pursue happiness, make money, and help other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also have a bunch of annoying biases though, and these biases often lead us to make the wrong choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of these calculations boil down at some level to the value of something we think we can gain, the value of something we think we might lose, and the probabilistic frequency of a decision turning out good or bad (how likely is it that something will go wrong, and how often would this happen).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three interesting biases are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loss aversion&lt;/strong&gt;: we think that we dislike losing things more than we actually do. People will usually spend or do more to avoid losing something that they have than they would spend or do to gain that thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inertia&lt;/strong&gt;: we generally prefer to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; do anything that changes the status quo too much, and specifically we prefer &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to make decisions if we think we can avoid them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frequency vs magnitude&lt;/strong&gt;: We&amp;rsquo;re generally bad at calculating the total value of a series of small decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Loss aversion&lt;/em&gt; is why people generally end up with more stuff than they want, and why self-storage is an $x$-trillion-dullar business. For physical stuff, it&amp;rsquo;s easy enough to compensate: just &amp;ldquo;lose&amp;rdquo; the thing you think you value for a few months and see how often you you needed it. For things like relationships, homes, jobs, it still exists but is harder to &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to learn to compensate for &lt;em&gt;inertia&lt;/em&gt; is to play speed chess. It pretty soon becomes obvious that one of the simplest winning strategies is to make decisions faster than your opponent and win on time. In chess, it&amp;rsquo;s very clear that making no decision is always the worst decision. In life, it can be a bit less clear-cut, but decisions which look like you can ignore when you actually can&amp;rsquo;t (ignoring them becomes an active decision on its own), become clearer when you think about &amp;ldquo;doing nothing&amp;rdquo; as watching your clock tick down towards certain loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taleb talks a lot about frequency loss in &amp;ldquo;Fooled by Randomness&amp;rdquo; (the only book of his that I would recommend). Most people would prefer to lose R365/year in a once-off unexpected event than to steadily lose R1/day in expected events (at least in slightly more complicated cases where the overall value isn&amp;rsquo;t instantly obvious). This is related to loss-aversion, but specifically for small, very frequent losses. We make lots of slightly risky decisions every day, where &amp;ldquo;losing&amp;rdquo; doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually mean that much, and most people are more loss-averse in these cases than accounted for just by &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; loss-aversion on its own. For small, frequent events, compensate harder by choosing the unsafe option more often, especially when the losses are limited and the choice comes up frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enjoyment vs Satisfaction</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/enjoyment-vs-satisfaction/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 21:36:21 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/enjoyment-vs-satisfaction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The English language is not known for being precise. People use the same words to mean very different things, often inconsistently. This confused language leads to confused thoughts, which leads people to make bad decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One example of this is are two different pleasurable feelings, which I&amp;rsquo;ll call &lt;em&gt;enjoyment&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;satisfaction&lt;/em&gt;, although most people use these fairly interchangeably. For now, let&amp;rsquo;s assume that enjoyment is a short-lived shallower emotion, while satisfaction lasts longer and is overall more desirable (another word with an imprecise meaning).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People say things like, &amp;ldquo;I really enjoy pizza&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;I really enjoy writing&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;I enjoy hiking&amp;rdquo;, but they mean pretty different things. Although it&amp;rsquo;s hard to generalize, it&amp;rsquo;s not uncommon for people to feel a short-lived positive emotion &lt;em&gt;while eating&lt;/em&gt; pizza, followed by a long-lived negative one a short time afterwards. On the other hand, it&amp;rsquo;s more common for people to feel short-lived negative emotions while writing (frustration) or hiking (exhaustion), but feel longer-lived positive emotions afterwards (pride, exhilaration).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s say that people enjoy eating pizza and find satisfaction by hiking up mountains (everyone is different, so choose your own examples that make more sense if necessary).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often conflate these meanings, and that&amp;rsquo;s strange because in a way they&amp;rsquo;re opposites. And because we conflate the meanings, we make bad decisions. We order pizza when we&amp;rsquo;re sad because through imprecise language we have come to associate the concept of pizza with the emotion that we experience after hiking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose the term &lt;em&gt;satisfaction&lt;/em&gt;, because this is another concept that we often understand poorly. We experience desire or need for satisfaction, and we try to satisfy or fulfil these desires. But again because of poor terminology, we fail to differentiate between two kinds of desire &amp;ndash; the desire for enjoyment and the desire for satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our desires for satisfaction &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be fulfilled. We experience the desire, we complete some action, and the desire goes away. Our desires for enjoyment &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; be fulfilled, but instead they grow into habits as we feed them. If you try to satisfy your desire to eat pizza by eating pizza, the desire will grow more frequent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s quite hard to differentiate between desires that can be fulfilled through action, and those that grow stronger when you attempt to fulfil them, but it&amp;rsquo;s pretty important to try and make this distinction as accurately as possible. There are also desires that fall in grey areas between enjoyment and satisfaction. For example, people who have a running habit might not enjoy running, but the runner&amp;rsquo;s rush is enough to keep them at it. Therefore, running can be like enjoyment (it&amp;rsquo;s a desire where the attempted fulfilment grows the desire into a habit), but also like satisfaction (it&amp;rsquo;s unenjoyable while you do it, but satisfying after).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you try fulfil a desire, try to classify into enjoyment or satisfaction first. Some, like &amp;ldquo;retail therapy&amp;rdquo; are obvious, and should be avoided, but they are engrained enough into society, with the help of marketing manipulation, that people don&amp;rsquo;t really notice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embracing the Paradox</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/embracing-the-paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 19:04:51 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/embracing-the-paradox/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;All models are wrong, but some are useful&amp;rdquo;, someone smart once said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common mistake people make is to have mental models in too few dimensions. This is understandable because thinking in multiple dimensions is a known human weakness. If you want to visualise something in 17 dimensional space, you have to visualise it in 3 dimensional space and say &amp;ldquo;17&amp;rdquo; to yourself repeatedly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I digress. Take introverts for example. Many people assume that introverts and extroverts are on opposite ends of a single dimension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introverts stay inside most of the time by themselves, and they sometimes make cool advancements in science. They get too obsessed about things that most people wouldn&amp;rsquo;t find interesting. They hate parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extroverts are the opposite. They love parties, and are often the centre of attention. They enjoy communicating with groups of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common way I hear people talking about this is by relating it to energy levels. An introvert is &amp;ldquo;drained&amp;rdquo; by people and needs to &amp;ldquo;recharge&amp;rdquo; by themselves after spending time in group settings. Extroverts are &amp;ldquo;energised&amp;rdquo; by people, and get depressed and drained when alone, needing to &amp;ldquo;recharge&amp;rdquo; by going out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not a psychologist, but this all seems like complete bullshit to me, and it makes far more sense to think about introvert/extrovert people on &lt;strong&gt;two&lt;/strong&gt; dimensions rather than one. Some people enjoy socialising in groups &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; spending large amounts of time alone. Some people dislike both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a two dimensional model, we can imagine &amp;ldquo;introvert&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;extrovert&amp;rdquo; as skills instead of opposites. Someone could learn to play the violin and the piano, and getting better at the violin wouldn&amp;rsquo;t make him worse at the piano. That seems obvious? So apply the same to introverts and extroverts. The thing that makes you tired is not some innate set of genes that makes you enjoy solitude or company. It&amp;rsquo;s practice. If you (I) do 100 push ups, you&amp;rsquo;d (I&amp;rsquo;d) be pretty damn exhausted, but if you (I) did it every day, it would soon(ish) be easy. Building skills makes them less tiring, and if something makes you tired you can actively work at it daily until it doesn&amp;rsquo;t any more. Like learning violin or how to do push ups, it probably helps a lot if you really want to learn how to spend time alone and/or in groups (the one you find hard), and preferably have a coach or teacher to give you some tips along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a simple example. It isn&amp;rsquo;t original because it&amp;rsquo;s just a worse version of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.inc.com/author/joshua-spodek&#34;&gt;Joshua Spodek&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; article. His is longer, better written and has pretty graphs, so read that rather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, once you&amp;rsquo;ve done this, it applies in far more cases than introversion/extroversion. Any time you have any tradeoff (I want to eat my cake and keep it), don&amp;rsquo;t get stuck asking which one you want &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt;, assuming that you have to sacrifice the other (opposite) option. Maybe they&amp;rsquo;re not opposite. Maybe you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; keep you cake and eat it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write down your tradeoff as a line with one option on the left extreme, and the other option on the right. Then draw a square below, and put the left option at the top left, and the right option at the bottom right. Now try to work out what some examples of having both and neither (those charts in Joshua&amp;rsquo;s article above really help if you&amp;rsquo;re not following) and fill out the bottom left and top right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now see what you need to do to get to the top right. To have your cake and keep it. It&amp;rsquo;s possible far more often than you think.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Problem With Going Independent</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/the-problem-with-independent/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 09:01:25 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/the-problem-with-independent/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You might know that I&amp;rsquo;m pretty critical of companies, jobs, bosses, etc. A good intro to some of these ideas is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.paulgraham.com/boss.html&#34;&gt;Paul Graham&amp;rsquo;s Essay&lt;/a&gt; on why we weren&amp;rsquo;t meant to have a &amp;ldquo;boss&amp;rdquo;. Children get introduced to the idea that someone else should tell you what to do and when to do it at a young age, but it is far from a natural or healthy way to live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you don&amp;rsquo;t want to have a boss, or a job that dictates which hours you&amp;rsquo;re allowed to spend with friends and family, there are plenty of role models out there to learn from. People who have become their own bosses, started profitable and popular companies of one. &lt;a href=&#34;https://levels.io/&#34;&gt;Pieter Levels&lt;/a&gt; started several popular internet sites and &lt;a href=&#34;http://nomadlist.io/open&#34;&gt;makes enough money&lt;/a&gt; from these even though he defies convention. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ajlkn?lang=en&#34;&gt;AJ&lt;/a&gt; did something similar at a smaller scale, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/patio11&#34;&gt;Patio11&lt;/a&gt; was a &amp;ldquo;work for yourself&amp;rdquo; champion until he joined Stripe, but he continues to write extensively about related topics. There are whole websites like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.indiehackers.com/&#34;&gt;Indie Hackers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.producthunt.com/&#34;&gt;Product Hunt&lt;/a&gt; built for people who gave up 9-5 and started creating their own products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t have a vision, idea, or simply don&amp;rsquo;t want to work alone on your own stuff all the time, you can also freelance or contract. There are a bunch of sites like CodeMentor, UpWork, etc where people post small jobs and have them done on a case-by-case basis. You can also work short contract, ranging from a couple of days to a couple of years, where you join a team and work for a boss as you would for an employee, but you know it&amp;rsquo;s short term and they don&amp;rsquo;t really &amp;ldquo;own&amp;rdquo; you to the same extent. You can make decent money doing these things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But - the largest problem I see with any of these routes, is that you risk complete knowledge and skill stagnation. Although starting your own business has a huge learning curve, and you&amp;rsquo;d learn a bunch about people, sales, marketing and all the &amp;ldquo;messy&amp;rdquo; parts of a tech business the first time, you&amp;rsquo;ll soon realise you don&amp;rsquo;t have any time to waste on trying &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; things. Most of the indie devs get stuck in fairly &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo; technology, like WordPress or PHP. They&amp;rsquo;ve built something before, and it worked, and they&amp;rsquo;re on tight timelines, so they&amp;rsquo;ll use it again. No problem here if you become Pieter Levels - PHP still works, still scales, and there&amp;rsquo;s nothing wrong with it. But if you don&amp;rsquo;t become that successful, it closes the Plan B exit, where you go give your knowledge for money again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I met a failed Pieter once. His product had failed due to drastic changes in other technology that he relied on. He was 40 and looking for a job. He was fairly desparate and wanted to join a dev team again. But he hadn&amp;rsquo;t worked in a team for over a decade, he wrote hacky outdated Python 2 code that worked, but was difficult to collaborate with and maintain. We coudln&amp;rsquo;t give him a job. He couldn&amp;rsquo;t find a job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you work for yourself, you won&amp;rsquo;t be treated as a resource, but you won&amp;rsquo;t be invested in like a resource either. Companies have changing needs and it&amp;rsquo;s harded to say &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo; to them than yourself. They&amp;rsquo;ll expect you to do new things that you aren&amp;rsquo;t comfortable with, but they&amp;rsquo;ll also make sure you have the time and resources you need to learn how (good companies anyway), and possibly people who have done it before to show you the ropes. If you go independent, you lose all of this, and you&amp;rsquo;ll probably put off learning that difficult thing forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-topics&#34;&gt;New topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generalising vs Specialising&lt;/strong&gt;: when does it pay to double down on your existing skills compared to learning new ones? Jack of all tradse and master of none? Or &amp;ldquo;that guy who can do stuff&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Being suspicious of hype while still keeping up with modern changes&lt;/strong&gt;: how far should you take &amp;ldquo;get off my lawn&amp;rdquo; when the young&amp;rsquo;uns come to you with their AI blockchains, and how far should you investigate and try these to see how much substance there is? Is there an inverse relation between your age and how much new stuff you want to try instinctively?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ethics of Fake It Till You Make It</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/fake-it-till-you-make-it-ethics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 09:12:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/fake-it-till-you-make-it-ethics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;People will tell you to fake it until you make it. You might find that slightly disturbing. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t the world have enough lying, over-confident people in it already? You&amp;rsquo;ve probably met that guy (let&amp;rsquo;s call him Guy) who says he can do everything, but can&amp;rsquo;t. Maybe people think he&amp;rsquo;s smart, but actually it&amp;rsquo;s all just a veneer of confidence, and as he walks through life causing trouble and producing bad quality output, he continues to cover everything in his oily confidence, and people continue to regard him as competent. You&amp;rsquo;ve decided that you want to be the opposite of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s fine, but it gets a bit more complicated. Let&amp;rsquo;s assume a work-related context for now &amp;ndash; you have a certain set of skills, and you want to provide valude to your employer, who gives you money each month. The best way you can do this is to provide as much context and information as possible about what you can and can&amp;rsquo;t do, and then to do the things in the overlap of &amp;ldquo;what needs to be done&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;what you can do&amp;rdquo;. Simple?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not really. Communicating your competence constantly takes time, and time is valuable. One of the ways you can provide value is by not wasting time. Already, there are tradeoffs to make. You can imagine some small task that you&amp;rsquo;re not super confident about, but you think you can pull it off. You could wait a few days until the person you need to communicate your doubts to is back, or you could just wing it and hope for the best. You estimate you have a 95% chance of &amp;ldquo;getting it right&amp;rdquo; and the deadlines are tight. They want it &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You do the thing. The thing turns out well. Everyone is happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slowly you realise that confidence &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; often the way that you provide value. Nobody really knew how to do The Thing, and in the end, the person who was most confident did The Thing. In general, it&amp;rsquo;s far more valuable to Do Things then to communicate every doubt you have about your ability to Do Things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what stops you being like our friend who abused his confidence? One part is &lt;em&gt;ownership&lt;/em&gt;. Even above being able to do things, being &lt;em&gt;willing&lt;/em&gt; to take responsibility for doubt is a hugely valuable thing to most people. A lot of time is wasted throughout business, government and other places by people searching for someone willing to take the blame for something &lt;em&gt;if it goes wrong&lt;/em&gt;. People don&amp;rsquo;t like being responsible for things that might go wrong. But, most things actually go right, so if you&amp;rsquo;re into a bit of gambling when the odds are in your favour, it probably makes sense to do a lot of The Things, and watch most of them Go Right, and a couple of them Go Wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What sets you apart from Guy, out slimey overconfident fraudster, is that you know and everyone else knows that you &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; The Things. They&amp;rsquo;re yours. If they go well, good. If they don&amp;rsquo;t, you apologise and set out a list of lessons to be learned, while Guy is already pushing the blame onto others at the first sign of any problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do things you can&amp;rsquo;t do, it&amp;rsquo;s the only way you learn how to do them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-topics&#34;&gt;New topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/strong&gt;: (wasn&amp;rsquo;t from list)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enjoyment vs Satisfaction&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Satisfaction is deeper and usually caused by things you don&amp;rsquo;t enjoy. Language is imprecise and people make Bad Life Choices because they don&amp;rsquo;t think about what words mean, or have clear mental concepts for specific words&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing (and publishing) 500 words per day</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/writing-500-words-per-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2019 20:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/writing-500-words-per-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t make any resolutions for 2019, but I would like this year to be one of building constructive habits. I skimmed some concepts in 2018 around the power of habit, and spent some time with ideas like &amp;lsquo;Do we spend too much time focusing on things topics like &lt;em&gt;Inspiration&lt;/em&gt; when most of what we achieve is actually driven by &lt;em&gt;self discipline&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;habit&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fell in and out of several good and bad habits during 2018, including a reading habit where I read a bunch of books, a note-taking habit where I took copious notes about each of these books, and a writing habit, where I worked each morning for an hour on writing technical tutorials, emails, or other ideas. I also used my fitbit on and off to re-inforce my walking habit, and averaged 15k steps a day for January 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like these to become stronger and better defined as soon as possible. Preferably from today. It&amp;rsquo;s easier to spend time on habits when I&amp;rsquo;m alone, but I&amp;rsquo;d like to find time even when I&amp;rsquo;m living with Isabel. Isabel went back to Europe today, so part of this output is probably driven by sudden loneliness and a bit of good old boredom, but I&amp;rsquo;d like to work out how to continue good habit even when I&amp;rsquo;m not alone, and also reduce bad habits like too much phone or social media use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, most of the 500 word daily snippets should be as close to publishable as possible. This means that they should be coherent, use full sentences, talk about an idea or topic that at least some people would find interesting, and preferably contain some humour. Unlike most blogging attempts and habits that I see, the posts should not be self-centered. All in all, the future posts should be very unlike this current one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I expect time to be limited and I don&amp;rsquo;t want to spend the time I have available searching for topics, I&amp;rsquo;ll maintain a list of topics to write about. I&amp;rsquo;ll add more than one item a day to this list, so that each day I&amp;rsquo;ll have a growing list of topics to pick from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I&amp;rsquo;ll set up a static page generator and website to learn more about how those work. I chose Hugo after some experimentation and found a very basic and minamilist &amp;ldquo;paper&amp;rdquo; theme which I quite like. Previously, I&amp;rsquo;ve written HTML by hand, or done fully dynamic applications using Django, Flask, or similar frameworks. I&amp;rsquo;m still looking for the perfect markdown editor. Typora is quite nice, but lacks command line integration. Vim is quite nice, but I keep losing stuff and I don&amp;rsquo;t enjoy typing in mono-spaced font. Hackmd is nice but I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be restricted to online only and I don&amp;rsquo;t know who maintains it so I don&amp;rsquo;t fully trust it. I&amp;rsquo;ll keep searching for something minimal and functional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, that&amp;rsquo;s 500 words. The topic list will start with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Miscalculating risks: why you should aim for small frequent losses&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;A rehash of Taleb&amp;rsquo;s idea that most people over-estimate the downside of losing a few dollars a day for the chance to win big, and under-estimate the downside of winning a few dollars a day while risking large losses, combined with Freakonomics idea that we over-bias towards &amp;ldquo;default&amp;rdquo; options &amp;ndash; e.g. if you&amp;rsquo;re not sure if you should quit your job, you probably should&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The problem of going independent&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;An explanation of why autonomy is great, and why we should be very suspicious of a system in which we are encouraged to voluntarily give up autonomy and take on a boss (link to PG&amp;rsquo;s boss essay), but also exploring the other side &amp;ndash; becoming independent and not being pushed to learn new things, with a high risk of being left with no advancement and a set of defunct skills&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>