<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gareth Dwyer</title>
    <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gareth Dwyer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 09:01:25 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Problem With Going Independent</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/the-problem-with-independent/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 09:01:25 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/the-problem-with-independent/</guid>
      <description>You might know that I&amp;rsquo;m pretty critical of companies, jobs, bosses, etc. A good intro to some of these ideas is Paul Graham&amp;rsquo;s Essay on why we weren&amp;rsquo;t meant to have a &amp;ldquo;boss&amp;rdquo;. Children get introduced to the idea that someone else should tell you what to do and when to do it at a young age, but it is far from a natural or healthy way to live.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ethics of Fake It Till You Make It</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/fake-it-till-you-make-it-ethics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 09:12:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/fake-it-till-you-make-it-ethics/</guid>
      <description>People will tell you to fake it until you make it. You might find that slightly disturbing. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t the world have enough lying, over-confident people in it already? You&amp;rsquo;ve probably met that guy (let&amp;rsquo;s call him Guy) who says he can do everything, but can&amp;rsquo;t. Maybe people think he&amp;rsquo;s smart, but actually it&amp;rsquo;s all just a veneer of confidence, and as he walks through life causing trouble and producing bad quality output, he continues to cover everything in his oily confidence, and people continue to regard him as competent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing (and publishing) 500 words per day</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/writing-500-words-per-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2019 20:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/writing-500-words-per-day/</guid>
      <description>I didn&amp;rsquo;t make any resolutions for 2019, but I would like this year to be one of building constructive habits. I skimmed some concepts in 2018 around the power of habit, and spent some time with ideas like &amp;lsquo;Do we spend too much time focusing on things topics like Inspiration when most of what we achieve is actually driven by self discipline and habit&amp;rsquo;.
I fell in and out of several good and bad habits during 2018, including a reading habit where I read a bunch of books, a note-taking habit where I took copious notes about each of these books, and a writing habit, where I worked each morning for an hour on writing technical tutorials, emails, or other ideas.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>