<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gareth Dwyer</title>
    <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gareth Dwyer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 17:20:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 Retrospective</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2018-retrospective/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 17:20:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/2018-retrospective/</guid>
      <description>This is a (late) 2018 retrospective. It&amp;rsquo;s mainly for personal use as I enjoy looking back and seeing how naive I was $n$ years ago, but I&amp;rsquo;ve enjoyed reading retrospectives from others in the tech community so I&amp;rsquo;m making it public without advertising it too widely.
The year of employment I took up full time employment at CoGrammar (formerly HyperionDev, a product we still run) in November 2017. As I&amp;rsquo;m still here, 2018 marks my first year ever of uninterrupted full time employment (I previously did two relatively long periods at AWS, but these were interleved between academic commitments).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inconsistent Ethics and Voting</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/inconsistent-ethics-and-voting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2019 23:06:37 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/inconsistent-ethics-and-voting/</guid>
      <description>Utilitarianism is an ethical framework that many people partially rely on. It&amp;rsquo;s the simplest form of ethics: if you want to know if some action is moral or not, just have a look at the result of that action, and then decide.
Should you give food to a starving person? Sure, it will result in the starving person not being hungry, which is a moral result, so therefore the charity is a moral action.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incentives and Trust</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/incentives-and-trust/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 23:29:33 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/incentives-and-trust/</guid>
      <description>Incentives seem very well understood. We have a whole bunch of natural sounding ideas, such as
 If you reward a person for a specific behaviour, you&amp;rsquo;ll encourage more of that behaviour. If you punish someone for a specific behaviour, you&amp;rsquo;ll encourage less of that behaviour. If you need someone to do something that they don&amp;rsquo;t want to do, you need to monitor them to make sure that they actually do it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Salary</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/salary/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 18:14:26 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/salary/</guid>
      <description>Salaries After the big #TalkPay movement a couple of years ago, and the related discussion that came up as a result, I thought people were more aware of the imbalance between employer and employee when it comes to salary negotiation. But I still see a lot of people who are very happy to answer this question straight up. You shouldn&amp;rsquo;t. Never name the first number in a salary negotiation, and never give up any information about your previous salaries either.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boredom</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/boredom/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2019 22:03:40 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/boredom/</guid>
      <description>People are afraid of boredom. They actively avoid having any time that is unscheduled. If they do find a brief moment of unscheduled time, they quickly focus on finding something to do (reading Twitter in the checkout queue).
Boredom isn&amp;rsquo;t really a negative emotion. It&amp;rsquo;s not like fear or dread or hate or pain. And even busy-bodies like it for brief moments, as long as you call it &amp;ldquo;relaxation&amp;rdquo;.
You get home from whatever chaotic thing seemed important at the time, and just do nothing for a while.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guardian vs Dale Carnegie</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/guardian-vs-dale-carnegie/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2019 09:23:50 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/guardian-vs-dale-carnegie/</guid>
      <description>The Guardian released a new donation campaign ages ago. The messages at the bottom of each article always look something like this.
(their highlight).
If you&amp;rsquo;ve read any Dale Carnegie or other pop-psychology of a &amp;ldquo;self help&amp;rdquo; kind of nature, the first advice you usually hear about getting other people to do things for you. These people will tell you to make sure you focus not on yourself but on the other person.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Technical Interviews</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/technical-interviews/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 13:05:27 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/technical-interviews/</guid>
      <description>Many programmers don&amp;rsquo;t like the style of technical interviews given by most companies. In these &amp;ldquo;whiteboarding&amp;rdquo; interviews, you are usually given a difficult problem from computer science in which you have to produce a program that can take some input and efficiently produce some related output. Usually, to pass these interviews, you need to have a deep understanding of algorithms and data structures, including graph traversal algorithms, tree data structures (maybe even the dreaded red-black tree, which is known for being very complicated and hard to understand intuitively), and dynamic programming.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hype</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/hype/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 19:16:43 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/hype/</guid>
      <description>People like hype. Hype is hard to identify when it&amp;rsquo;s happening, and is easy to identify with hindsight. Hype can last for different amounts of time - anything from minutes to decades.
Hype in the world of technology is bad. A recurring theme is people getting very excited about some new technology and spending thousands of hours learning about it, building programmes or even whole schools around it, and over-saturating the market without producing much value.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk Calculation and Human Biases</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/risk-calculation-and-human-biases/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2019 09:08:47 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/risk-calculation-and-human-biases/</guid>
      <description>Most days that you live through, you do some kind of risk calculations. We&amp;rsquo;re seldom certain about anything, so we learn to estimate probabilities based on a wide range of knowledge and experiences, and hope for the best.
Most of us humans get pretty good at this, and we use this risk calculation skill to stay alive, pursue happiness, make money, and help other people.
We also have a bunch of annoying biases though, and these biases often lead us to make the wrong choices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enjoyment vs Satisfaction</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/enjoyment-vs-satisfaction/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 21:36:21 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/enjoyment-vs-satisfaction/</guid>
      <description>The English language is not known for being precise. People use the same words to mean very different things, often inconsistently. This confused language leads to confused thoughts, which leads people to make bad decisions.
One example of this is are two different pleasurable feelings, which I&amp;rsquo;ll call enjoyment and satisfaction, although most people use these fairly interchangeably. For now, let&amp;rsquo;s assume that enjoyment is a short-lived shallower emotion, while satisfaction lasts longer and is overall more desirable (another word with an imprecise meaning).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embracing the Paradox</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/embracing-the-paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 19:04:51 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/embracing-the-paradox/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;All models are wrong, but some are useful&amp;rdquo;, someone smart once said.
A common mistake people make is to have mental models in too few dimensions. This is understandable because thinking in multiple dimensions is a known human weakness. If you want to visualise something in 17 dimensional space, you have to visualise it in 3 dimensional space and say &amp;ldquo;17&amp;rdquo; to yourself repeatedly.
But I digress. Take introverts for example.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Problem With Going Independent</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/the-problem-with-independent/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 09:01:25 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/the-problem-with-independent/</guid>
      <description>You might know that I&amp;rsquo;m pretty critical of companies, jobs, bosses, etc. A good intro to some of these ideas is Paul Graham&amp;rsquo;s Essay on why we weren&amp;rsquo;t meant to have a &amp;ldquo;boss&amp;rdquo;. Children get introduced to the idea that someone else should tell you what to do and when to do it at a young age, but it is far from a natural or healthy way to live.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ethics of Fake It Till You Make It</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/fake-it-till-you-make-it-ethics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 09:12:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/fake-it-till-you-make-it-ethics/</guid>
      <description>People will tell you to fake it until you make it. You might find that slightly disturbing. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t the world have enough lying, over-confident people in it already? You&amp;rsquo;ve probably met that guy (let&amp;rsquo;s call him Guy) who says he can do everything, but can&amp;rsquo;t. Maybe people think he&amp;rsquo;s smart, but actually it&amp;rsquo;s all just a veneer of confidence, and as he walks through life causing trouble and producing bad quality output, he continues to cover everything in his oily confidence, and people continue to regard him as competent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing (and publishing) 500 words per day</title>
      <link>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/writing-500-words-per-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2019 20:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sixhobbits.github.io/hugoblog/posts/writing-500-words-per-day/</guid>
      <description>I didn&amp;rsquo;t make any resolutions for 2019, but I would like this year to be one of building constructive habits. I skimmed some concepts in 2018 around the power of habit, and spent some time with ideas like &amp;lsquo;Do we spend too much time focusing on things topics like Inspiration when most of what we achieve is actually driven by self discipline and habit&amp;rsquo;.
I fell in and out of several good and bad habits during 2018, including a reading habit where I read a bunch of books, a note-taking habit where I took copious notes about each of these books, and a writing habit, where I worked each morning for an hour on writing technical tutorials, emails, or other ideas.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>